華納兄弟電影公司
派拉蒙電影公司
傳奇電影公司
辛克匹製片公司
星 際 穿 越
我父親是個農民
Well, my dad was a farmer.
那時候大家都是農民
Um, like everybody else back then.
當然他最初並非如此
Of course, he didn't start that way.
電腦顯示傾斜角度太大
Computer says you're too tight.
- 不 我能行的 - 正在穿越直道
- Nah, I got this. - Crossing the Straights.
- 正在關閉引擎 Cooper - 不
- Shutting it down, Cooper. - No!
- 關閉所有引擎 - 不 要加大馬力
- Shutting it all down. -No, I need power up!
爸爸
Dad?
抱歉 Murph 回去睡吧
Sorry, Murph. Go back to bed.
- 我以為你是那個幽靈 - 不
- I thought you were the ghost. - No.
世上沒有幽靈 寶貝
There are no such things as ghosts, babe.
外公說有幽靈的
Grandpa says you can get ghosts.
也許那是因為外公
Maybe that's because Grandpa's
自己就快變成幽靈了 回去睡吧
close to being one himself. Back to bed.
你又夢到那次墜機了嗎
Were you dreaming about the crash?
快回去睡覺 Murph
Get your butt back in bed, Murph.
小麥都死光了
The wheat had died.
枯萎病肆虐 我們只能全部燒掉
The blight came and we had to burn it.
只剩下玉米 我們種了幾畝玉米
And we still had corn. We had acres of corn.
還有 漫天的沙塵暴
But, uh, mostly we had dust.
我沒法準確描述 這風沙持續不斷
I guess I can't describe it. It was just constant.
日復一日 塵土飛揚
Just that steady blow of dirt.
我們會用布條
We wore, um, little strips of sheet...
掩住口鼻
...sometimes over our nose and mouth...
防止吸入過多塵土
...so that we wouldn't breathe so much of it.
佈置餐桌的時候 我們總是把盤子反扣過來放
When we set the table, we always set the plate...
倒扣過來放 水杯啊 茶杯啊 不管是什麼
...upside-down. Glasses or cups, whatever it was...
都倒扣著放
...upside-down.
快點 Murph 動作快點
Shake a leg! Murph, get a move on!
Tom 下午四點 跟我去穀倉學習怎麼用除草劑
Tom, four o'clock today, you and me in the barn, Herbicide Resistance 101.
- 好嗎 - 遵命
- Check? -Yes, sir.
別拿到餐桌上
Not at the table, Murph.
爸爸 你能修好嗎
Dad, can you fix this?
你怎麼把登月艙搞成這樣
What the heck did you do to my lander?
不是我
Wasn't me.
我猜猜 是你的幽靈幹的
Let me guess. It was your ghost?
幽靈把它從書架撞下來了 還總把書弄掉
It knocked it off my shelf. It keeps knocking books off.
根本沒有幽靈 傻瓜
No such thing as ghosts, dumb-ass.
我查過了 這叫搗蛋鬼
I looked it up. It's called a poltergeist.
爸爸 告訴她
Dad, tell her.
好吧 這不是很科學 Murph
Well, it's not very scientific, Murph.
你說過科學就是確定我們未知的事物
You said science was about admitting what we don't know.
沒話說了吧
She's got you there.
嘿 先把我們的東西看好再說
Hey, start looking after our stuff.
Coop
Coop.
好吧 Murph 你想聊科學嗎
All right, Murph, you want to talk science?
不要只告訴我你害怕幽靈
Don't tell me you're afraid of some ghost.
不 你要更加深入
No, you got to go further.
你需要記錄現象
You got to record the facts,
進行分析 發現其中的原理
analyze, get to the how and the why...
最後得出結論 好嗎
...then present your conclusions. Deal?
- 好的 - 很好
- Deal. - All right.
- 好好上課 - 等等
- Have a good day at school. - Hold up.
今天有家長會 是家長
Parent-teacher conferences. Parent.
不是家長的家長
Not grandparent.
別著急 小子
Slow down, turbo!
- 那不是沙塵暴吧 - 是Nelson在燒他的莊稼
- That's not a dust storm. - Nelson's torching his whole crop.
枯萎病嗎
Blight?
他們說這是最後一撥秋葵了
They're saying it's the last harvest for okra.
再也沒有了
Ever.
他應該跟我們一樣種玉米
He should've planted corn like the rest of us.
對Hanley小姐友善一點 她是單身
Now, be nice to that Miss Hanley. She's single.
這話是什麼意思
What's that supposed to mean?
為人類繁衍做貢獻 是你盡力的時候了 年輕人
Repopulating the earth. Start pulling your weight, young man.
你還是管好自己的事兒吧 老人家
Why don't you start minding your own business, old man?
好了 Murph 掛二檔
All right, Murph, give me second.
好
Uh-huh.
三檔
Third.
- 找檔啊 笨蛋 - 用力
- Find a gear, dumb-ass. - Grind it!
閉嘴 Tom
Shut it, Tom!
- 你幹了什麼 Murph - 她什麼也沒幹
- What'd you do, Murph? - Ah, she didn't do nothing.
- 車胎爆了而已 - 墨菲定律
- Blew a tire is all. - Murphy's Law.
閉嘴
Shut up!
- 去把備胎拿出來 Tom - 那個就是備胎
- Grab the spare, Tom. - That is the spare.
去拿補胎工具
Get the patch kit!
我們在這兒怎麼補
How am I supposed to patch it out here?
你自己想辦法
You got to figure it out.
我不可能一直在你身邊幫你的
I'm not always gonna be here to help you.
怎麼了 Murph
What's going on, Murph?
為什麼你和媽媽要用不好的事給我取名
Why did you and Mom name me after something that's bad?
我們沒有
We didn't.
墨菲定律呢
Murphy's Law?
墨菲定律並不是說會有壞事發生
Murphy's Law doesn't mean that something bad will happen.
而是說只要有可能的事 就一定會發生
What it means is whatever can happen will happen.
而這聽起來沒什麼不好
And that sounded just fine with us.
上車
Get in.
上車 我們走
Get in, let's go.
車胎還沒補好呢
What about the flat tire?
太棒了
Yeah.
那是一架印度空軍的無人機
It's an Indian Air Force drone.
太陽能電池夠整個農場用的
Solar cells could power an entire farm.
你來開 Tom
Take the wheel, Tom.
快快快
Go, go, go!
對準那架飛機
Keep that aimed right at it.
開快點 Tom 我們要跟丟了
Faster, Tom. I'm losing it.
對準點兒
Right at it.
保持住
Stay on it.
搞定了
Here we go.
真不錯 Tom
Nice one, Tom.
爸爸
Dad?
馬上就好了 不要停 不要停
I almost got it. Don't stop. Don't stop!
爸爸
Dad!
Tom
Tom!
是你讓我一直開的
You told me to keep driving.
有句老話怎麼說來著
Well, I guess that answers the
我讓你開下懸崖你也去啊
old "If I asked you to drive off a cliff" Scenario.
- 我們跟丟了 - 不 沒有
- We lost it. -No, we didn't.
想試試讓它盤旋一圈嗎
Want to give it a whirl?
這樣
This way.
來吧
Go.
讓它在那兒降落 就在水庫岸邊
Let's lay her down right there at the edge of the reservoir.
幹得漂亮
Nicely done.
你估計它飛了多久了
How long you think it's been up there?
德里飛行指揮中心關閉了 跟我們的一樣
Delhi Mission Control went down, same as ours...
十年前
...ten years ago.
所以飛了十年了
So for ten years?
- 它為什麼會飛這麼低呢 - 不知道
- Why did it come down so low? - I don't know.
也許是太陽把它烤傻了 也許它是在找什麼
Maybe the sun cooked its brain or it was looking for something.
- 什麼 - 給我大號的螺絲刀
- What? - Give me a large flatblade.
也許是找什麼信號 我不知道
Maybe some kind of signal? I don't know.
你打算拿它怎麼辦
What are you gonna do with it?
我準備讓它來給社會做點貢獻
I'm gonna give it something socially responsible to do...
比如驅動聯合收割機
...like drive a combine.
我們就不能放了它嗎
Can't we just let it go?
它又沒有傷害任何人
It wasn't hurting anybody.
這東西也需要適應時代 Murph
This thing needs to learn how to adapt, Murph...
就像我們一樣
...like the rest of us.
接下來怎麼樣 你們倆一起來嗎
How's this work? You guys come with?
我有課
I've got class.
她嘛 需要等等
This one needs to wait.
- 你幹什麼了 - 你進去他們就會告訴你了
- What did you do? - They'll tell you about it in there.
- 那我會生氣嗎 - 不是生我的氣
- Am I gonna be mad? - Not with me.
- 求你了 儘量別生氣 - 嘿 放鬆
- Just please try not to. - Hey. Relax.
我搞得定
I got this.
你遲到了 Coop
Little late, Coop.
是啊 我的車爆胎了
Yeah, we had a flat.
然後順便到亞洲戰鬥機商店逛了一圈
And I guess you had to stop off at the Asian fighter plane store.
不 其實 那是一架無人偵察機
No, actually, sir, that's a surveillance drone.
太陽能電池性能特別好 是印度的
With outstanding solar cells. It's Indian.
請坐吧
Take a seat.
那麼
So, uh...
Tom的成績出來了
...we got Tom's scores back.
他會成為一個非常棒的農民
He's going to make an excellent farmer.
是的 他確實挺有天賦 那大學呢
Yeah, he's got a knack for it. What about college?
大學的錄取名額非常少
The university only takes a handful.
教育資源稀缺
They don't have the resources to--
我一直在交稅
I still pay my taxes.
那些錢都去哪兒了 現在又沒有軍隊
Where's that money go? There's no more armies.
反正沒有用到大學教育上
Well, it doesn't go to the university.
聽著 Coop 你得現實一點
Look, Coop, you have to be realistic.
你現在就把我兒子拒之大學門外了嗎
You're ruling my son out for college now?
- 他才15歲 - Tom的分數不夠上大學的
- The kid's 15. - Tom's score simply isn't high enough.
你腰圍多少 32嗎
What's your waistline? About what, 32?
- 褲腿33嗎 - 我不知道你什麼意思
- About a 33 inseam? - I'm not sure I see what you're getting at.
需要兩組數位才能
It takes two numbers to measure
測量你的屁股 一次成績就決定我兒子的未來嗎
your ass but only one to measure my son's future?
別這樣 你是受過高等教育的人 Coop
Come on. You're a well-educated man, Coop.
- 一個飛行員 - 還是工程師
- And a trained pilot. - And an engineer.
沒錯 但是現在我們不需要工程師了
Okay, well, right now we don't need more engineers.
我們缺少的不是
We didn't run out of
電視和飛機 我們缺少的是食物
television screens and planes. We ran out of food.
世界需要農民 像你這樣的好農民
The world needs farmers. Good farmers, like you.
- 還有Tom - 沒受過教育的農民
- And Tom. - Uneducated farmers.
我們是守護地球的一代
We're a caretaker generation,
Coop 情況正在好轉
Coop. And things are getting better.
也許你的孫輩
Maybe your grandkids
- 能成為工程 - 說完了嗎 先生
- will get to be engin-- - Are we done here, sir?
沒有
No.
Hanley小姐還要談談Murph
Miss Hanley's here to talk about Murph.
Murph是個好孩子 很聰明
Murph is a great kid. She's really bright.
但她最近惹了一些麻煩
But she's been having a little trouble lately.
她把這個帶到學校給同學看
She brought this in to show the students.
關於登月的這章
The section on the lunar landings.
這是我的舊課本
Yeah, it's one of my old textbooks.
她很喜歡裡面的圖片
She always loved the pictures.
這是舊的聯邦教科書
It's an old federal textbook.
我們已經用修正過的版本替代它了
We've replaced them with the corrected versions.
修正過的
Corrected?
解釋了阿波羅計畫
Explaining how the Apollo
是我們偽造的 目的是迫使蘇聯破產
missions were faked to bankrupt the Soviet Union.
你不相信我們登過月
You don't believe we went to the moon'?
我相信這是非常聰明的政治策略
I believe it was a brilliant piece of propaganda.
讓蘇聯把資源都浪費在
The Soviets bankrupted themselves pouring resources...
火箭和沒用的機器上
...into rockets and other useless machines.
沒用的機器
"Useless machines."
如果我們不想重蹈
If we don't want a repeat of the
二十世紀過度浪費的覆轍 那麼
excess and wastefulness of the 20th century, then...
我們就必須教孩子們
...we need to teach our kids
認識這個星球 而不是想著離開它
about this planet, not tales of leaving it.
那些沒用的機器中
One of those useless machines
有一種叫核磁共振儀
they used to make was called an MRI.
哪怕還剩下一台
If we had any of those left,
醫生們就能及時發現
the doctors would've been able to find...
我妻子腦內的囊腫
...the cyst in my wife's brain
而不是在她死後
before she died instead of afterwards.
那麼坐在這裡聽這些話的人就會是她而不是我了
Then she'd have been the one listening to this instead of me...
那樣會更好一點 因為她一直都
...which would have been a good thing, because she was always...
比我冷靜
...the calmer one.
你妻子的事我很抱歉
I'm sorry about your wife, Mr. Cooper.
但是Murph跟幾個同學
But Murph got into a fistfight
打了起來 就因為這些
with several of her classmates over this...
阿波羅的無稽之談
...Apollo nonsense.
所以我們覺得應該把你找來
So we thought it best to bring you in and see what ideas...
和你溝通一下
...you might have for
看看從家長的方面該如何教育她
dealing with her behavior on the home front.
是啊 知道嗎 明天晚上有一場比賽
Yeah, you know what? Um, there's a game tomorrow night.
她最近特別喜歡棒球
She's going through a bit of a baseball phase.
有她最喜歡的球隊
Her favorite team is playing.
到時候會有糖果 汽水
There's gonna be candy and soda and...
我帶她去看比賽吧
I think I'll take her to that.
談得怎麼樣
How'd it go?
你這幾天不用上學了
I got you suspended.
什麼
What?
我是Cooper 請講
This is Cooper. Go.
Coop 你改裝的聯合收割機出故障了
Coop, those combines you rebuilt went haywire.
重置一下控制器就好了
Just reset the controllers.
我重置了 但你得回來看看
I did that. Now you should come take a look.
它們接二連三地離開田地跑到這兒來
One by one they've been peeling off the fields and heading over.
有什麼東西干擾了指南針
Something's interfering with the compass.
磁場或者什麼
Magnetism or some such.
掉下來的書沒有什麼特別之處
Nothing special about which book.
我一直在研究 像你說的
I've been working on it, like you said.
- 我數了這些空格 - 為什麼
- I counted the spaces. - Why?
如果幽靈想要傳達什麼資訊呢
In CASE the ghost is trying to communicate.
我在試摩爾斯電碼
I'm trying Morse.
摩爾斯電碼
Morse?
是的
Yeah.
- 點和線 用來 - 我知道摩爾斯電碼是什麼 Murph
- Dots and dashes, used-- - I know what Morse code is, Murph.
我只是不認為你的書架想跟你說話
I just don't think your bookshelf's trying to talk to you.
重置了所有指南針
Had to reset every compass
和定位系統才消除異常
clock and GPS to offset for the anomaly.
- 什麼異常 - 我不知道
- Which is? - I don't know.
如果房子建在了金屬礦上
If the house was built on magnetic ore...
第一次開拖拉機的時候我們就會發現的
...we'd have seen this the first time we switched on the tractor.
聽說你在學校的談話不是很順利
I hear your meeting at the school didn't go so well.
你聽說了
You heard?
我們似乎已經迷失自我了 Donald
It's like we've forgotten who we are, Donald.
我們是探索者 是先驅 而不是守護者
Explorers, pioneers, not caretakers.
當我還是個孩子的時候
When I was a kid...
感覺每天都有新的發明
...it felt like they made something new every day. Some...
新的小玩意兒 新的想法 每天都像過聖誕
...gadget or idea. Like every day was Christmas.
但那時有六十億人口
But six billion people...
你想像一下
...just try to imagine that.
每個人都想擁有一切
And every last one of them trying to have it all.
現在這個世界並不算太壞
This world isn't so bad.
Tom會過得很好
And Tom will do just fine.
不屬於這個時代的人是你
You're the one who doesn't belong.
晚生了40年或者早了40年
Born 40 years too late, or 40 years too early.
我女兒懂 上帝保佑她
My daughter knew it, God bless her.
你的孩子也懂 特別是Murph
And your kids know it. Especially Murph.
我們過去常常仰望星空
Well, we used to look up in the sky and wonder...
思考自身的存在
...at our place in the sTARS.
而現在我們只能擔心如何在沙塵暴中生存下去
Now we just look down and worry about our place in the dirt.
Cooper 你有你的專長
Cooper, you were good at something...
卻從沒得到機會施展
...and you never got a chance to do anything with it.
我很遺憾
I'm sorry.
沒人預料到
You didn't expect...
這片賜予我們糧食的土地
...this dirt that was giving you this food...
會轉頭攻擊你 毀滅你
...to turn on you like that and destroy you.
我記得那是在四月 四月十五號
In April-- I believe I'm right-- Fifteenth of April, I think.
大約是在一點半的時候
This happened about 1:30 when that thing...
沙塵暴出現在峽谷上
...came off the top of that canyon.
我那時候的球手才是真正的球手
In my day, we had real ballplayers.
這都哪來的笨蛋
Who are these bums?
我那時候 人人都忙著
In my day, people were too busy...
搶食物 誰還會去打棒球啊
...fighting over food to even play baseball.
看球賽吃爆米花 太彆扭了 我想吃熱狗
Popcorn at a ballgame is unnatural. I want a hot dog.
學校說你會跟隨我的腳步
School says you're gonna follow in my footsteps.
我覺得這很不錯
I think that's great.
- 你覺得這很不錯嗎 - 你討厭種地 爸爸
- You think that's great? - You hate farming, Dad.
外公說的
Grandpa said.
外公這麼說的嗎
Grandpa said, huh?
聽著 關鍵是你自己覺得怎麼樣
Listen, all that matters is how you feel about it.
我喜歡你的職業
I like what you do.
我喜歡我們的農場
I like our farm.
你會幹得非常出色的
You're gonna be great at it.
我們走吧
Let's get out of here.
這沙塵真猛
All right, it's a doozy.
大家都把口罩戴上
All right, gang, let's mask up.
- Tom Murph 好了嗎 - 好了
- Tom? Murph? Check'? - Yeah.
Murph Tom 你們的窗戶都關上了吧
Murph, Tom, you guys shut your windows?
Murph
Murph?
是幽靈
The ghost.
拿上你的枕頭
Grab your pillow.
去跟Tom一起睡
You're sleeping in with Tom.
這不是幽靈
It's not a ghost.
是引力
It's gravity.
我先送Tom上學 然後去鎮上
I'm dropping Tom, then heading to town.
你們倆介意收拾一下嗎 等你們禱告完以後
You want to clean that up when you've finished praying to it?
不是摩爾斯電碼 Murph 是二進位
It's not Morse, Murph. It's binary.
寬的是1 窄的是0
Thick is one, thin is zero.
是座標
Coordinates.
不是
Nope.
這裡
Here we go.
Thirty-three.
就是這兒
That's it.
我也要去
I can't miss this!
外公幾個小時後就會回來 Murph
Grandpa will be back in a couple hours, Murph.
但是你還不知道會發現什麼呢
But you don't know what you're gonna find.
所以
And that...
我就更不能帶你去了
...is why I can't take you.
Murph
Murph?
外公一會兒就回來了
Grandpa will be home in a while.
告訴他我會用無線電給他打電話
Tell him I'll call him on the radio.
- 啊 - 天哪
- Aah! -Jesus.
你在幹嗎
What are you doing?
噢 你覺得這很好玩是嗎
Oh, you think this is funny? Huh?
要不是我你根本不會在這兒
You wouldn't be here if it wasn't for me.
那就幫點忙
Make yourself useful.
嘿 Murph
Hey, Murph?
Murphy
我想路就到這兒了
I think this is the end of the road.
你不是帶了老虎鉗嗎
Didn't you bring the bolt cutters?
真是我女兒
That's my girl.
不許靠近柵欄
Step away from the fence!
別開槍 我沒有武器 我女兒在車上
Don't shoot! I'm not armed. My daughter's in the car.
請不要害怕
Don't be afraid.
北美防空聯合司令部
你怎麼找到這個地方的
How did you find this place?
我女兒在哪兒
Where's my daughter?
我有這裡的座標
You had the coordinates for this
標記在你的地圖上 你是從哪兒搞到的
facility marked on your map. Where did you get them?
我女兒呢
Where's my daughter?
別讓我再把你放倒 坐下
Don't make me take you down again. Sit down!
你還覺得你是海軍陸戰隊的嗎 夥計
Oh, you still think you're a Marine, pal?
海軍陸戰隊早就沒了
Marines don't exist anymore.
你這種傢伙挺適合幫我去割草
And I got grunts like you mowing my grass.
你從哪兒得到的座標
Where did you find those coordinates?
不過你看起來不像割草機
But you don't look much like a lawnmower.
我只能大材小用 把你改成吸塵器了
Think I'll turn you into an overqualified vacuum cleaner.
不 你不會的
No, you won't.
TARS 下去吧
TARS, back down, please.
你徵用前軍用設備可是要冒很大風險的
You know, you're taking a risk using ex-military security.
太舊了 而且控制單元非常不穩定
They're old, and their control units are unpredictable.
政府就只能提供這些
It's what the government could spare.
你是誰
Who are you?
Brand博士
Dr. Brand.
我認識一位元Brand博士 他是個教授
I knew a Dr. Brand once. He was a professor.
我不像一個教授嗎
What makes you think I'm not?
確實不像 也不可愛
Wasn't near as cute, either.
拜託 Brand博士 我不知道這是什麼情況
Please, Dr. Brand. I don't have any idea what this is.
我很擔心我女兒 只想她能在我身邊
Now I'm scared for my daughter and want her by my side.
你把我女兒帶來 我什麼都告訴你
You give me that, I'll tell you anything you want to know.
把負責人和那個女孩兒帶到會議室
Get the principals and the girl in the conference room, please.
你女兒沒事
Your daughter is fine.
她很聰明
Bright kid.
她媽媽一定也很聰明
Must have a very smart mother.
很明顯你們不想要任何到訪者
It's pretty clear you don't want any visitors.
那為什麼不放我們回到圍欄那裡
So why don't you just let us back up from your fence
我們會自己離開的
and we'll be on our way? Huh?
- 沒這麼簡單 - 就這麼簡單
- It's not that simple. - Well, sure, it is.
我根本不認識你
I don't know anything about you.
對這個地方也一無所知
I don't know anything about this place.
不 你知道
Yes, you do.
爸爸
Dad!
拉撒路
你好 Cooper
Hello, Cooper.
Brand教授
Professor Brand.
解釋一下你是怎麼找到這裡的
Explain to me how you found this facility.
是個意外
Kind of an accident.
無意之中發現的 我們在搜集廢棄物品
We sort of stumbled upon it. We were on a salvage run--
你正坐在全世界最隱蔽的地方
You're sitting in the best-kept secret in the world.
沒人能夠意外找到這裡 也沒人能隨便離開
Nobody stumbles in here. Nobody stumbles out.
Cooper 拜託
Cooper, please.
配合一下這些人
Cooperate with these people.
聽著
Look.
這很難解釋
It's kind of hard to explain.
我們找到這個座標是因為一個異常現象
We learned these coordinates from an anomaly.
什麼異常現象
What sort of anomaly?
我不想說那是超自然現象
I hesitate to term it supernatural,
但那確實不符合科學規律
but it definitely wasn't scientific.
你得說得更具體一點 Cooper先生 就現在
You're going to have to be specific, Mr. Cooper. Right now.
是引力異常
It was gravity.
是什麼樣的引力異常現象 在哪兒
Um, what sort of gravitational anomaly? Where was this?
我很高興你對這個問題這麼感興趣
Now, I'm real happy that you're excited about gravity, but...
但我不會說的
...but you're not getting
除非你們能給我保證
any answers from us until I get assurances.
- 保證 - 是的
- Assurances? - Yeah.
比如 保證我們離開這裡
Like, that we're getting out of here.
而且不是被裝進後備箱那種
And I don't mean in the trunk of some car.
你不知道我們是誰嗎 Coop
Don't you know who we are, Coop?
不 教授 我不知道
No, professor, I don't.
你認識我父親 Brand教授
You know my father, Professor Brand.
我們是NASA的
We're NASA.
NASA 美國國家航空航天局
- NASA - NASA.
- NASA. - NASA.
你效力過的那個NASA
The same NASA you flew for.
我聽說你們部門被關閉了 先生
I heard they shut you down, sir...
因為你們拒絕從平流層往下投炸彈
...for refusing to drop bombs from the stratosphere...
投向挨餓的人們
...onto starving people.
當他們意識到濫殺群眾
When they realized that killing other people was...
並不是長久之計的時候 就把我們又召回來了
...not a long-term solution, then they needed us back.
- 秘密地 - 為什麼要保密
- In secret. - Why secret?
因為公眾
Because public opinion
不允許花錢在宇宙探索上
wouldn't allow spending on space exploration.
尤其是當人們還填不飽肚子的時候
Not while you're struggling to put food on the table.
枯萎病
Blight.
七年前殺死了小麥 今年是秋葵
Wheat seven years ago. Okra this year.
現在只剩下玉米了
Now there's just corn.
可我們種的比以往還多
And we're growing more than we ever have.
但就像愛爾蘭的
But like the potatoes in
土豆和沙塵暴裡的小麥一樣
Ireland and the wheat in the Dust Bowl...
玉米 也會絕跡
...the corn will die.
很快
Soon.
我們會找到辦法的 教授 總會有辦法的
We'll find a way, professor. We always have.
就憑地球屬於人類這個堅定的信念嗎
Driven by the unshakable faith the Earth is ours.
地球不單是我們的
Not just ours, no.
但這裡是我們的家
But it is our home.
地球的大氣層80%都是氮氣
Earth's atmosphere is 80 percent nitrogen.
可我們不呼吸氮氣
We don't even breathe nitrogen.
但枯萎病菌呼吸氮氣 所以當它越來越猖獗
Blight does. And as it thrives,
空氣裡的氧氣就會越來越少
our air gets less and less oxygen.
經歷過饑餓的這一波人將會面臨窒息
The last people to starve will be the first to suffocate.
你女兒這代人
And your daughter's generation...
將是這個地球上的最後一代
...will be the last to survive on Earth.
Murph有點累了
Murph is feeling a little tired.
能不能讓她在我的辦公室睡一會兒
I was wondering if she could take a nap in my office.
好 謝謝
Yeah. Thank you.
好了
Okay.
現在告訴我 你們拯救世界的計畫是什麼
...now you need to tell me what your plan is to save the world.
我們不是要拯救這個世界 而是要離開它
We're not meant to save the world. We're meant to leave it.
漫遊者
Rangers.
這是在軌道上
The last components of our
一艘多功能船永恆號的最後一個元件
one versatile ship in orbit, the Endurance.
我們最後的遠征
Our final expedition.
你派人去外太空尋找新的居住地
You sent people out there looking for a new home?
拉撒路行動
The Lazarus missions.
拉撒路 聖經中的人物 病死後第四日復活 被視為耶穌神跡的表現
拉撒路（Lazarus）
《聖經•約翰福音》中記載的人物
他病危時沒等到耶穌的救治就死了
但耶穌一口斷定他將復活
四天后拉撒路果然從山洞裡走出來
證明了耶穌的神跡
- 哦 聽起來真了不起 - 死而復生的拉撒路
- Oh, that sounds cheerful. - Lazarus came back from the dead.
對 死而復生 那就得先死
Sure, but he had to die in the first place.
太陽系沒有
There's not a planet in
適合人類生存的星球
our solar system that could sustain life...
系外最近的行星卻在一千光年之外
...and the nearest star's over a thousand years away.
這根本是無謂的掙扎
That doesn't even qualify as futile.
你將他們送去哪裡了
Where'd you send them?
Cooper
Cooper...
我只能告訴你這麼多了 除非你同意
...I can't tell you anymore unless you agree...
來駕駛飛船
...to pilot this craft.
你曾經是我們最好的宇航員
You're the best pilot we ever had.
我也就到過平流層
I barely left the stratosphere.
這些人連模擬艙都沒出過
This team never left the simulator.
我們需要宇航員
We need a pilot, and this
你以前的訓練就是為了這個
is the mission that you were trained for.
我訓練的時候可不知道有這麼個計畫
Without even knowing it?
一個小時前
An hour ago, you didn't
你都不知道我還活著 計畫不還在進行中嗎
even know I was alive. You were going anyway.
我們別無選擇
We had no choice.
但你來到了這兒
But something sent you here.
- 他們選擇了你 - 他們是誰
- They chose you. - Who's "They"?
我要去多久
How long would I be gone?
很難說 幾年
Hard to know. Years?
我有孩子 教授
I've got kids, professor.
到太空去 拯救他們
Get out there and save them.
他們是誰
Who's "They"?
我們從五十年前就開始探測到引力異常現象
We started detecting gravitational anomalies almost 50 years ago.
多數是小的畸變
Mostly small distortions
在大氣層上層的儀器中
to our instruments in the upper atmosphere.
事實上 我相信你自己也曾經遇到過
In fact, I believe you encountered one yourself.
是的 在直道上
Yeah, over the Straights.
那次事故 控制系統受到了外力干擾
My crash. Something tripped my fly-by-wire.
正是
Exactly.
但在所有的異常現象中 最為顯著的是
But of all these anomalies, the most significant is this:
在土星附近
Out near Saturn...
時空發生了畸變
...A disturbance of space-time.
- 那是蟲洞嗎 - 四十八年前出現的
- Is that a Wormhole? - It appeared 48 years ago.
它通向哪裡
And it leads where?
另一個星系
Another galaxy.
蟲洞不會自然形成
A wormhole's not a naturally occurring phenomenon.
是有人放在那裡的
Someone placed it there.
- 他們嗎 - 嗯
- "They"? - Mm.
不論他們是誰 很顯然他們是在幫助我們
And whoever they are, they appear to be looking out for us.
通過蟲洞 我們能前往其他星球
That Wormhole lets us travel to other sTARS.
出現得非常及時
It came along right as we needed it.
他們將宜居的世界 放在了我們觸手可及的地方
They've put potentially habitable worlds right within our reach.
十二個 這是我們初步探查的結果
Twelve, in fact, from our initial probes.
- 你們派了探查器嗎 - 嗯
- You sent probes into that? -Mm-hm.
我們是派人去的 十年前
We sent people into it. Ten years ago.
拉撒路行動
The Lazarus missions.
十二個可能的世界
Twelve possible worlds...
十二架漫遊者飛船
...twelve Ranger launches carrying...
載著最勇敢的人
...the bravest humans ever to live...
由了不起的Mann博士帶隊
...led by the remarkable Dr. Mann.
每個人的著陸艙裡攜帶著兩年的補給
Each person's landing pod had enough life support for two years.
當然 他們可以用休眠來延長時間
But they could use hibernation to stretch that...
這樣對有機體的觀察時間可以長達十年或更久
...making observations on organics over a decade or more.
他們的任務是對所到之地進行評估
Their mission was to assess their world,
倘若發現可行性
and if it showed potential...
就發射信號
...then they could send out a signal,
然後進入休眠 等待救援
bed down for the long nap, wait to be rescued.
如果那裡沒有生存條件呢
And what if the world didn't show promise?
所以要勇敢
Hence the bravery.
你們沒有足夠資源去探查十二個地方
You don't have the resources to visit all 12.
對
No.
以通過蟲洞的資料傳輸為基礎
Data transmission back through the Wormhole is rudimentary.
每年用簡單的二進位方式進行分析
Simple binary pings on an annual basis
我們得到了一些線索 哪些地方存在可能
give us some clue as to which worlds have potential.
有一個很有希望的星系
And one system shows promise.
就一個 不覺得風險有點大嗎
One. That's a bit of a long shot, isn't it?
一個星系 要是有三個可能的地方
One system with three potential worlds?
已經不錯了
No long shot.
好吧
Okay.
假設找到一個地方
So if we find a home...
- 然後呢 - 那才是真正的賭注
- ...then what? - That's the long shot.
有個A計畫 還有個B計畫
There's a Plan A and a Plan B.
你發現發射室有什麼奇怪的地方嗎
Did you notice anything strange about the launch chamber?
整個設施就是個大型離心機
This entire facility's a centrifuge.
是運輸工具 還是空間站
Some kind of vehicle. A space station?
都是 這是A計畫
Both. Plan A.
那怎麼離開地面呢
How do you get it off the ground?
第一次引力異常 顛覆了一切
The first gravitational anomalies changed everything.
我們明白了利用引力的可行性
Suddenly we knew that harnessing gravity was real.
於是我開始研究一個推論
So I started working on a theory
並且建造了這個空間站
and we started building this station.
但你還沒有驗證這個推論
But you haven't solved it yet.
所以才要有B計畫
That's why there's Plan B.
問題是地心引力
The problem is gravity. How to
如何才能把一定數量的人類帶離這個星球
get a viable amount of human life off the planet.
這是一個辦法
This is one way.
B計畫 超級人口炸彈
Plan B, a population bomb.
超過五千個受精卵 整體重量不超過九百公斤
Over 5,000 fertilized eggs weighing in at just under 900 kilos.
怎麼養育它們
How would you raise them?
飛船上有設備 我們會先孵化十個
With equipment on board, we incubate the first 10.
這之後 用代孕的方式 讓人口指數倍增
After that, with surrogacy, the growth becomes exponential.
三十年後 就會有幾百人的殖民地了
Within 30 years, we could have a colony of hundreds.
不過殖民的真正難題是遺傳多樣性
The real difficulty with colonization is genetic diversity.
就靠這個解決了
This takes care of that.
那這裡的人怎麼辦
But what about the people here? You just...
就這麼放棄他們嗎
...give up on them?
我的孩子們
My kids?
所以 A計畫更好一些
That's why Plan A is a lot more fun.
- 進展到什麼程度了 - 差不多了
- How far have you got? - Almost there.
你要我放棄擁有的一切
You're asking me to hang everything...
去賭一個"差不多"
...on an almost.
我要你相信我
I'm asking you to trust me.
為我們找個新家
Find us a new home.
等你回來的時候
And by the time you return...
我就已經解決了引力的問題
...I will have solved the problem of gravity.
我向你保證
I give you my word.
走開
Go away!
Murph
Murph.
走開 你要走就走吧
Go! If you're leaving, just go.
這世界沒讓你滿足過 對嗎 Coop
This world was never enough for you, was it, Coop?
怎麼 就因為飛向太空
What, because heading out
是我心中與生俱來的使命
there is what I feel like I was born to do?
並且讓我激動不已嗎
And it excites me? Heh.
不 我覺得那沒有錯
No, that does not make it wrong.
未必
It might.
不要相信因為錯誤理由做出的正確事情
Don't trust the right thing done for the wrong reason.
做任何事情之前 都要搞清楚為什麼
The why of the thing, that's the foundation.
理由很充分
And the foundation's solid.
我們農民 就這樣坐著
We farmers, we sit here
每年要是沒有下雨 我們就會說
every year when the rains fail and we say:
明年吧
"Next year."
可是 明年救不了我們 後年也一樣
Well, next year ain't gonna save us, nor the one after that.
這裡曾是一片沃土 Donald
This world's a treasure, Donald,
但現在卻在逼迫我們離開
but it's been telling us to leave for a while now.
人類起源於此 並不意味著要結束於此
Mankind was born on Earth, it was never meant to die here.
Tom會沒事的
Tom will be all right,
但你要跟Murph好好說清楚
but you got to make things right with Murph.
我會的
I Will.
別隨便作出不能履行的承諾
Without making promises you don't know you can keep.
你得跟我談談 Murph
You have to talk to me, Murph.
走之前我得把這事解決了
I need to fix this before I go.
那我就不讓你解決 你就可以留下了
Then I'll keep it broken so you have to stay.
你們倆出生之後
After you kids came along,
你媽媽跟我說過一句話 我一直都沒弄明白
your mom said something to me I never quite understood.
她說 現在
She said, "Now...
我們就是孩子們以後的回憶了
...we're just here to be memories for our kids."
現在我明白她的意思了
And I think that now I understand what she meant.
一旦為人父母 你就成了孩子們未來的幽靈
Once you're a parent, you're the ghost of your children's future.
你說過幽靈不存在的
You said ghosts didn't exist.
沒錯 Murph
That's right, Murph.
Murph 看著我
Murph, look at me.
我現在還不能當你的幽靈
I can't be your ghost right now.
我必須存在
I need to exist.
他們選擇了我
They chose me.
Murph 他們選擇了我 你看到了 是你把我領向他們的
Murph, they chose me. You saw. You're the one who led me to them.
所以你更不能去了
That's exactly why you can't go.
我破譯那個資訊了
I figured out the message.
- 一個詞 你知道是什麼嗎 - Murph
- One word. Know what it is? - Murph.
留下
"Stay."
- 它說留下 爸爸 - Murph
- It says, "Stay," Dad. - Murph.
你不相信我
You don't believe me.
看看這些書 看看這裡 它說留下
Look at the books! Look at this. It says, "Stay."
你為什麼不聽我說呢 它說留下
Why--? You're not listening! It says, "Stay!"
不 我會回來的
No, I'm coming back.
什麼時候
When'?
一個給你 一個給我
One for you, one for me.
當我在外太空深度休眠
When I'm up there in hypersleep, or...
或是光速航行
...traveling near the speed of light, or...
或是接近黑洞的時候
...near a black hole...
我的時間會發生變化 會比平常慢很多
...time's gonna change for me. It's gonna run more slowly.
等我們回來之後
When we get back...
我們來比比看
...we're gonna compare.
- 我們的時間會不一樣嗎 - 是的
- Time will run differently for us? - Yeah.
等我回來的時候
By the time I get back,
我倆也許一樣大 你和我
we might even be the same age, you and me.
怎麼回事 想想看
"What?" Imagine that!
啊 Murph
Aw, Murph...
你不知道你什麼時候才能回來
You have no idea when you're coming back.
完全不知道
No idea at all!
Murph 不要讓我就這樣離開
Murph, don't-- Don't make me leave like this.
拜託 Murph
Come on, Murph!
不要讓我這樣離開 Murph
Don't make me leave like this, Murph!
嘿
Hey...
我愛你
...I love you.
永遠 聽到了嗎
Forever. You hear me?
我會永遠愛你 我會回來的
I love you forever, and I'm coming back.
我一定會回來的
I'm coming back.
- 談話還好嗎 - 很好
- How'd it go? - Fine.
非常好
Just fine.
我愛你 Tom
I love you, Tom.
- 一路平安 好嗎 - 好
- Travel safe, huh? - Yeah.
幫我照看我們的家 好嗎
You look after our place for me, all right?
- 好嗎 - 嗯
- All right? - Uh-huh.
嘿 我能開你的車嗎
Hey, can I use your truck
- 你不在的時候 - 你是說你的車嗎
- while you're gone? - You mean your truck?
我會讓他們把車開回來的
I'll make sure they bring it back.
照顧好孩子們 Donald
Look after my kids, Donald!
主引擎準備啟動 倒計時 十
Go for main engine start. T-minus 10...
- 爸爸 - 九
- Dad! -...nine...
爸爸
Dad!
八
...eight...
七
...seven...
爸爸
Dad!
六
...six...
五 主引擎啟動 四
...five, main engine start, four...
三
...three...
二
...two...
一 助推器點火
...one. Booster ignition and...
引擎狀態良好 啟動自帶控制程式
All engines look good. Beginning roll program.
準備進行一級分離程式
Prepare for stage one separation.
開始分離
Stage one.
現在是我做主了
There is my command.
大家還好嗎 在我機器人政權下的奴隸們
Everybody good? Plenty of slaves for my robot colony?
它有內置的幽默功能
They gave him a humor
好讓它跟大家更和諧
setting so he'd fit in better with his unit.
它以為這樣能給大家減壓
He thinks it relaxes us.
一個巨大的毒舌機器人
A giant sarcastic robot.
真是個好主意
What a great idea!
如果你喜歡 我可以在開玩笑的時候亮個提示燈
I have a cue light I can use when I'm joking if you like.
這倒有點兒用
That'd probably help.
你可以用它找到回來的路
You can use it to find your way
在我把你轟出氣閘之後
back to the ship after I blow you out the airlock.
- 你的幽默指數是多少 TARS - 100%
- What's your humor setting, TARS? - That's 100 percent.
麻煩你調到75%吧
Let's bring it on down to 75, please.
現在完成二級分離
Stage two separation.
信號傳輸改為手動
All feeds going manual.
改為手動
Going manual.
關閉加熱器 一 二 三
Deactivate probe heater one, two and three.
完成
Check.
- 我接手控制 - 控制權已交給你
- Taking control. - This is handover to you.
- 測向器 正常 - 收到
- A.D.F. Check. - Over.
推進器減速 燃料艙 一 二 三
Pull thrusters back. Fuel cells one, two, three.
狀態100%
One hundred percent.
一切正常
Ex-mites.
離開很艱難
It's hard leaving everything.
我的孩子們 你的父親
My kids. Your father.
我們會一起度過一段漫長的時光
We're going to be spending a lot of time together.
- 我們得學會交流 - 還有沉默
- We should learn to talk. - And when not to.
我只是實話實說
Just being honest.
也沒必要這麼誠實吧
I don't think you need to be that honest.
嗨 TARS 你的誠實指數是多少
Hey, TARS, what's your honesty parameter?
- 90% - 90%
- Ninety percent. - Ninety percent?
絕對誠實不見得是最圓滑的 或
Absolute honesty isn't always the most diplomatic, nor the...
最安全的交流方式 對情感動物來說
...safest form of communication with emotional beings.
好吧
Okay.
那就90% Brand博士
Ninety percent it is, Dr. Brand.
我們在接近永恆號 還有十二分鐘
We are coming up on the Endurance. Twelve minutes out.
好的 接管控制
Okay. Taking control.
接近艙門 距離五百米
Approaching module port, 500 meters.
看你的了 Doyle
It's all you, Doyle.
慢慢來 Doyle 慢慢來
Nice and easy, Doyle. Nice and easy.
感覺很不錯
I feel good.
來吧
Take us home.
- 鎖定 - 目標鎖定
- Lock. - Target locked.
- 好樣的 - 好了 戴上頭盔
- Well done. - Okay, helmets on.
幹得好
Good job.
門沒加上電
Door's not charging.
沒關係
Never mind.
Cooper 你應該能控制了
Cooper, you should have control.
開始控制
Control here.
與環型艙的通訊已經啟動
Communication with ring module active.
程式啟動
That's initiate.
- 可以開始旋轉了嗎 - 稍等一下
- Are we ready to spin? - Just a sec.
- 你好 CASE - 你好 TARS
- Hello, CASE. - Hello, TARS.
好了 都準備好了
All right, we're all set.
我們開始吧
All right, let's do it.
旋轉30%
Thirty percent of spin.
一個引力加速度
One G.
你們的引力感覺怎麼樣
How's gravity treating you back there?
很好
Well.
Romilly 你還好嗎
Romilly? Hey, you okay?
- 還好 - 沒事吧
- Yeah. - You all right?
嗯 過一會兒就好了
Mm. Yeah, I just need a minute.
在休眠艙裡有暈海寧
We have some Dramamine in the hab pod,
可能在冰匣裡 我去拿
or maybe in the cryo-beds. I'll just be a sec.
- 嘿 Brand - 什麼
- Hey, Brand? - Yeah?
多拿點兒
Bring a lot.
Amelia 多保重
Amelia, be safe.
- 向Mann博士轉達我的問候 - 好的 爸爸
- Give my regards to Dr. Mann. - I will, Dad.
航行軌跡看起來不錯
It looks good for your trajectory.
按我們計算 到土星需要兩年
We've calculated two years to Saturn.
暈海寧可真多
That's a lot of Dramamine.
請照顧好我的家人 好嗎 先生
Look after my family, will you, please, sir?
我們會一直等著你們歸來
We'll be waiting for you when you get back.
年紀長了 智慧長了 重逢的喜悅不變
A little older, a little wiser, but happy to see you.
不要溫順地走進那個良夜
作者：狄蘭•湯瑪斯
生卒：1914年-1953年
簡介：英國作家、詩人
英國詩人狄蘭湯瑪斯於20世紀中期創作的詩歌
不要溫順地走入那長夜
Do not go gentle into that good night
白日將盡 暮年仍應燃燒咆哮
Old age should burn and rave at close of day
怒斥吧 怒斥那光明漸逝
Rage, rage against the dying of the light
智者深知 人之將死 黑暗自有其時
Though wise men at their end Know dark is right
因為他們所言 未曾裂天如電
Because their words had forked No lightning they
不要溫順地走入那長夜
Do not go gentle into that good night
怒斥吧 怒斥那光明漸逝
Rage, rage against the dying of the light
- 沒事吧 - 還好
- You good? - Yeah.
沒事 謝謝
Okay, thank you.
給你 藥片
Here. Pills.
真孤單
So alone.
我們至少還有彼此 Mann博士可慘多了
We have each other. Dr. Mann had it worse.
我是說他們
No, I mean them.
這是個完美的星球 再也找不到像它這樣的了
It's a perfect planet, and we won't find another one like her.
對 這可不像搬家找房子
No, it's not like looking for a new condo.
人類將會
The human race is going to be...
漂泊流亡
...adrift...
不顧一切去尋找
...desperate for a rock
一個可供生存的地方
it can cling to while it catches its breath.
這正是我們的使命
We need to find that rock.
而我們的三個目標
And our three prospects are at the edge of what...
處於可維持人類生命的邊緣
...might sustain human life.
Laura Miller的星球是第一個
Laura Miller's planet is first.
Laura是我們生物學專案的開啟者
Laura started our biology program.
- Wolf Edmunds在這裡 - 說說Edmunds吧
- Uh, Wolf Edmunds is here. - Tell me about Edmunds.
呃 他是個粒子物理學家
Oh, uh, Wolf's a particle physicist.
他們都沒有家人 對嗎
None of them had families, huh?
對 不能有牽掛 我父親堅持的
No. No attachments. My father insisted.
他們都知道
They all knew the odds
再次見到人類的機會很渺茫
against ever seeing another human being again.
希望我們能讓至少三個感到驚喜
I'm hoping we can surprise at least three of them.
- Mann博士呢 - Mann博士
- How about Mann? - Dr. Mann?
他很了不起 是我們中最棒的
He's remarkable. He's the best of us.
他帶領十一個人
He inspired 11 people to follow
踏上了人類歷史上最孤獨的旅程
him on the loneliest journey in human history.
科學家 探險家
Scientists, explorers.
我最愛的也是這點 我們雖然會面對種種困難
That's what I love. You know, out there we face great odds.
甚至死亡
Death, but...
但不會有邪惡
...not evil.
你不認為自然是邪惡的
You don't think nature can be evil?
不 很殘酷 很恐怖 但
No. Formidable. Frightening. But...
絕不是邪惡
...no, not evil.
因為獅子把羚羊撕碎 它就邪惡嗎
Is a lion evil because it rips a gazelle to shreds?
只是我們自己的感覺而已
Just what we take with us, then.
對
Yeah.
這一組人代表了最優秀的人類
This crew represents the best of humanity.
也包括我嗎
Even me, huh?
知道嗎 我們90%同意
You know what? We agreed, 90 percent.
感激不盡
There you go.
- 別待著了 - 就待一會兒
- Don't stay up. - I'll be there in a minute.
記著 Coop 現在空氣有限 吸一口少一口
Just remember, Coop, you are literally wasting your breath.
嘿 TARS 我們再研究一遍航行軌跡
Hey, TARS? Let's go over that trajectory one more time.
八個月到火星
Eight months to Mars.
通過引力彈弓效應加速 十四個月到土星
Counter-orbital slingshot around. Fourteen months to Saturn.
什麼都沒變
Nothing's changed on that.
我問你一件事
Just let me ask you something.
Brand博士和Edmunds
Dr. Brand and Edmunds--
幹嘛要竊竊私語 他們又聽不見
Why are you whispering? They can't hear you.
Brand博士和Edmunds 他們很親近嗎
Dr. Brand and Edmunds. They close?
我不知道
I wouldn't know.
是不知道
Is that 90 percent "Wouldn't
還是不能說
know" Or 10 percent "Wouldn't know"?
我還有酌情處置功能 Cooper
I also have a discretion setting, Cooper.
可惜是張撲克臉 小子
But not a poker face, Slick.
嘿 孩子們
Hey, guys.
爸爸馬上就要去睡大覺了
Uh, Dad's about to go down for the long nap.
想在睡前跟你們再聊一會兒
So I wanted to give you an update.
從這裡看地球真奇妙
The Earth looks amazing from here. Um...
看不見任何塵土
You can't see any of the dust. Heh.
希望你們兩個都好好的
Um, I really hope you guys are doing great.
我知道你們肯定能收到這段視頻
I know you'll get this message.
Brand教授跟我保證過 會讓你們看到
Professor Brand's assured me he'll get it to you.
記住 我愛你們
Know that I love you.
- 是爸爸嗎 - 應該不是 Murph
- Is it him? - I don't think so, Murph.
你一定是Donald
You must be Donald.
你好 Murph
Hello, Murph.
你為什麼開著我爸爸的車
Why are you in my dad's truck?
他讓我開回來給你哥哥
He wanted me to bring it for your brother.
他給你們傳了一段視頻
He sent you a message.
他的離開讓她很難過
She's pretty upset with him for leaving.
你們也可以錄些東西
If you record any messages,
由我傳送給Cooper
I can get them to transmit it to Cooper.
Murph像朵耀眼的火花
Murph is a bright spark.
也許我能再加把火
Maybe I should fan the flame.
她的老師已經感覺力不從心了
She's already making fools of her teachers.
所以也許她應該來給你們出出難題
So maybe she should come and make a fool out of you.
- 他們現在在哪兒 - 前往火星的路上
- So where are they? - Heading for Mars.
你們下次聽到Cooper的消息時
The next time you hear from Cooper,
他們應該在去土星的路上了
they'll be coming up on Saturn.
學校方面 他們想讓我重修植物病理學
As far as school goes the administration wants me to repeat Plant Pathology.
真討厭
Which sucks.
不過 我可以提前一年學習高等農業
But they said I could start Advanced Agriculture a year early.
好了 我得走了 爸爸 你多保重
All right, I got to go, Dad. Hope you're safe up there.
抱歉 Coop
Um, sorry, Coop.
我叫Murph來打個招呼 但是她和你一樣固執
I asked Murph to say hi, but she's as stubborn as her old man.
我下次再試試吧
I'll try again next time.
你沒事吧 Rom
You all right, Rom?
這太恐怖了 Cooper
This gets to me, Cooper.
瞧 這兒
This. This.
我們被幾毫米的鋁板保護著 然後就什麼也沒有了
Millimeters of aluminum, that's it, and then nothing...
在太空裡 我們可能瞬間就會沒命
...out there for millions of miles won't kill us in seconds.
你知道嗎 很多世界上頂尖的
You know that some of the finest...
單人帆船運動員都不會游泳
...solo yachtsmen in the world don't know how to swim?
他們不會游泳
They don't know how.
一旦落水 他們就完蛋了
And if they go overboard, psst, they're done.
我們是探險家 Rom
We're explorers, Rom.
這就是我們的船
This is our boat.
給
Here.
這是探測器傳過來的嗎
This is from the, uh, relay probe?
蟲洞附近的軌道傳過來的
It was in orbit around the Wormhole.
這裡是蟲洞 每當我們經過這裡的時候
This is the Wormhole, and every time we'd come around...
都會收到
...we would receive images
從外星系的另一端傳過來的圖像
from the other side of the foreign galaxy.
就像一個擺動的潛望鏡
Oh, yeah. Like swinging a periscope around.
正是
Exactly.
所以我們很快就會知道
So we got a pretty good idea
另一邊是什麼樣的了 對嗎
what we're gonna find on the other side, huh?
航向上來說 是的
Navigationally.
夥計們 我們將在大約三小時後接近蟲洞
Guys? We'll be approaching the Wormhole in about three hours.
嘿 Coop
Hey, Coop?
能停止旋轉嗎
Can we stop the spinning?
為什麼
Why?
因為我們已經近得可以看見它了
Because we're close enough to see it now?
好的
All right.
謝謝
Thanks.
那兒 就是它 蟲洞
There, that's it! That's the Wormhole!
說話別噴口水 Rom
Say it, don't spray it, Rom.
是球狀的
It's a sphere.
當然是球狀的 你以為
Of course it is. What, you--?
難道你以為是個洞嗎
You thought it would just be a hole?
不 只是所有我見過的插圖 都是
No, it's just that all the illustrations I've ever seen, they...
那些插圖是為了解釋它的原理
In the illustrations, they're trying to show you how it works.
如果說你要從這裡到那裡
So they say you want to go from here to there.
太遠了 對吧
But it's too far, right?
蟲洞可以把空間像這樣折疊起來
So a Wormhole bends space like this,
於是你可以抄近路了
so you can take a shortcut through...
從更高的緯度
...A higher dimension.
所以
Okay, so...
為了展現這個原理
...to show that, they've turned
他把三維空間換成二維空間
three-dimensional space into two dimensions...
於是蟲洞在二維空間就成了 圓
...which turns a Wormhole into two dimensions, a circle.
圓在三維空間是什麼
What's a circle in three dimensions?
- 球體 - 沒錯
- A sphere. - Exactly.
球狀的洞
A spherical hole.
是誰放在那裡的 我們該感謝誰呢
But who put it there? Who do we have to thank?
我誰也不謝
I'm not thanking anybody
除非我們能從這裡完整地出去
until we get out of here in one piece, Rom.
有什麼訣竅嗎 Doyle
Any trick to this, Doyle?
沒人知道
No one knows.
其他人都過去了 對吧
The others made it, right?
至少有幾個過去了
At least some of them.
大家準備跟我們的太陽系說再見吧
Everybody ready to say goodbye to our solar system?
沒準兒是銀河系
To our galaxy.
開始吧
Here we go.
控制器在這裡沒有用 我們正在穿越高維空間
The controls won't work here. We're passing through the bulk.
這裡超過了三維
It's space beyond our three dimensions.
我們能做的只有記錄和觀察
All you can do is record and observe.
那是什麼
What is that?
我覺得就是他們
I think it's them.
是時空彎曲效應
Distorting space-time.
不 不要
Don't! Don't!
剛剛那是怎麼回事
What was that?
第一次握手
The first handshake.
我們
We're...
我們到了
We're here.
失聯的通訊資料傳送過來了
So the lost communications came through.
- 怎麼傳過來的 - 這邊的記憶體緩存了下來
- How? - The relay on this side cached them.
只是這些年的基礎資料 沒什麼特別
So years of basic data. No real surprises.
Miller的信號一直持續著
Miller's site has kept pinging thumbs up,
Mann博士的也是
as has Dr. Mann's. Um...
Edmunds的三年前就消失了
Edmunds' went down three years ago.
因為傳輸失敗嗎
Transmitter failure?
也許吧 失聯之前他一直在傳送信號
Maybe. He was sending the thumbs up right until it went dark.
但是Miller的信號還是很強
But Miller's still looks good though, right?
因為我們正在靠近她
Because she's coming up fast.
不過有個麻煩的情況
With one complication.
這星球離卡岡圖亞比我們預計的要近
The planet is much closer to Gargantua than we thought.
- 卡岡圖亞 - 我們這麼稱呼黑洞
- Gargantua? - It's what we're calling the black hole.
Miller和Mann博士的星球都繞著它旋轉
Miller's and Dr. Mann's planets both orbit it.
Miller的已經處於臨界點
And Miller's is on the horizon?
就像在籃筐邊緣停留的籃球
As a basketball around a hoop.
在那裡登陸會讓我們非常接近黑洞
Landing there takes us dangerously close.
那麼大的黑洞會產生巨大的引力
And a black hole that big has a huge gravitational pull.
聽著 我可以利用那顆中子星來抵消黑洞的引力
Look, I could swing around that neutron star to decelerate.
不 不是這個 是時間的問題
No, it's not that. It's time.
那個星球的引力
The gravity on that planet will
會讓我們的時間比地球慢很多
slow our clock compared to Earth's drastically.
有多慢
How bad?
那個星球上的一小時相當於
Every hour we spend on that planet will be...
地球上的七年
...seven years back on Earth.
天哪
Jesus.
這就是相對論 夥計們
Well, that's relativity, folks.
好吧 我們不能就這樣登陸而不
Well, we can't just drop down there without...
Cooper 我們有任務
Cooper, we have a mission.
對 Doyle 我們是有任務 我們的A計畫
Yeah, Doyle, we have a mission, and our mission Plan A is...
是找到一個星球
...to find a planet that can
使之成為現在地球上那些人的新家
habitate the people that are living on Earth now.
你不能只想著家人
You can't just think about your family.
你得放眼大局
Now you have to think bigger.
我想的是
I am thinking about my
我的家人和成千上萬的家庭 好嗎
family and millions of other families, okay?
等執行計畫的時候
Plan A does not work if the
人都已經死光了 那A計畫就沒有任何意義
people on Earth are dead by the time we pull it off.
不 不會的
No. It doesn't.
所以我們有B計畫
That's why there's a Plan B.
好吧 Cooper是對的
Okay. Cooper's right.
我們得把時間也當成一種資源
We need to think of time as a resource,
就像氧氣和食物 下去是有代價的
like oxygen and food. Going down will cost us.
聽我說
All right, look.
Mann博士的資料看起來很不錯
Dr. Mann's data is promising,
但是我們得花幾個月才能到那兒
but it will take months to get there.
Edmunds的就更遠了
And Edmunds', it's even further.
Miller的消息不多
Miller hasn't sent much, but what
但她說的很有希望 有水 有機物
she has is very promising. It's water, it's organics...
- 這可不是每天都能找到的 - 對 沒錯
- You don't find that every day. - No, you don't.
再想想將要消耗的資源 包括時間
And just think about the resources, including time...
在試圖回到這裡的過程中
...that would be spent trying to get back here.
- Romilly - 什麼
- Romilly... - Yeah?
我們要離Miller的星球多遠
...how far off from Miller's
才能避免時間發生轉變
planet do we have to be to stay out of the time shift?
只要離開波峰就行
Just back from the cusp.
那就是這裡 在Miller星球的上空
All right, which is here, just outside of Miller's planet.
- 沒錯 - 好
- Right. - Okay.
這兒是卡岡圖亞 這兒是Miller的星球
Here's Gargantua. Here's Miller's planet.
我們不能
Instead of taking the
繞著Miller的星球軌道
Endurance into orbit around Miller's planet...
那樣雖然節省燃料 但會消耗大量的時間
...which would conserve fuel, but we would lose a lot of time...
要是我們繞卡岡圖亞走更大的軌道
...what if we take a wider orbit around Gargantua,
與Miller的星球平行
parallel with Miller's planet...
避開時間變化區 到這裡
...outside of this time shift, to here?
然後我們開漫遊者下去 把Miller和她的樣本接來
Then we take the Ranger down, we get Miller, we get her samples.
回來進行分析詢問 一進一出
We come back, we analyze, we debrief. We're in, we're out.
儘管費點燃料 但節省了很多時間
We lose a little fuel, but we save a whole lot of time.
- 這樣能行 - 計畫不錯
- That'll work. - That's good.
到了那裡可就沒時間瞎扯聊天了
There's no time for monkey business or chit-chat down there.
所以 TARS 你必須留在這裡
So, TARS, you should definitely stay here.
CASE 你跟我走 別人都可以留下
CASE, you're with me. Anyone else can stay.
如果你們要去幾年的話
If we're talking about a couple years,
我可以利用這個時間研究引力
I could use the time to research gravity.
觀察蟲洞 這對Brand教授來說意義重大
Observations from the Wormhole, that's gold to Professor Brand.
TARS 找一條卡岡圖亞的軌道
TARS, factor an orbit of Gargantua.
節省燃料 少用推進器
Conserve fuel, minimize thrusting,
但要確保在Miller星球的範圍內
but make sure we stay in range of Miller's planet.
- 明白嗎 - 我不會丟下你的
- You got it? - I wouldn't leave you behind...
Brand博士
...Dr. Brand.
- 準備好了嗎 CASE - 是的
- You ready, CASE? - Yup.
- 你不太愛說話 是嗎 - 有TARS說就夠了
- You don't say much, do you? - TARS talks plenty for both of us.
脫離
Detach.
Romilly 看到引力值了嗎
Romilly, are you reading these forces?
難以置信
It's unbelievable.
真正的黑暗之心
A literal heart of darkness.
如果我們可以看到坍塌在裡面的星球
If we could just see the collapsed star inside...
看到奇點 就能解決引力的問題了
...the singularity, yeah, we'd solve gravity.
我們什麼都得不到嗎
And we can't get anything from it?
沒有什麼能從那兒離開
Nothing escapes that horizon.
連光都不行
Not even light.
答案就在那裡 卻沒辦法看見
The answer's there, just no way to see it.
這就是Miller的星球
There's Miller's planet.
再見 漫遊者
Goodbye, Ranger.
這比進入大氣層要快
This is fast for atmospheric entry.
- 需要用推進器來減速嗎 - 不
- Should we use the thrusters to slow? - No.
不 我要用漫遊者的空氣動力學來節省燃料
I'm gonna use the Ranger's aerodynamics to save some fuel.
空氣制動
Air brake?
我們要快速著陸
We want to get down fast,
- 不是嗎 - 我們要安全著陸
- don't we? - We want to get there in one piece.
- 坐穩 - Brand Doyle 準備好
- Hang on. - Brand, Doyle, get ready.
- 我們應該減速 - 待在那兒別動 CASE
- We should ease! - Hands where I can see them, CASE.
我唯一的一次事故
The only time I went down was
就是因為在錯誤的時間減速
when a machine was easing at the wrong time.
- 小心一點 - 也能讓你送命 跟魯莽駕駛一樣
- A little caution-- - Can get you killed, like reckless driving.
- Cooper 速度太快了 - 我能搞定
- Cooper, it's too damn fast! - I got this.
- 要關掉聲音回饋嗎 - 不 我需要感受氣流
- Should I disable the feedback? - No. I need to feel the air.
好了
Here we go.
全都是水
It's just water!
生命的要素
The stuff of life.
一千二百米
Twelve hundred meters.
- 能找到目標點嗎 - 鎖定
- Do we have a fix on the beacon? - Got it!
- 你能操作嗎 - 我得調整速度
- Can you maneuver? - I'll need to shave some speed.
我要螺旋式下降 大家坐穩
I'm gonna spiral down on top of it. Everybody hang on!
七百米
Seven hundred.
等我指令 CASE 等我指令
On my cue, CASE. On my cue.
五百米
Five hundred meters.
點火
Fire!
姿勢很優雅
Very graceful.
不
No.
但是很有效率
But very efficient.
你們還等什麼呢 走啊
What are you waiting for? Let's go!
走 走 走
Go, go, go!
這裡一個小時七年 分秒必爭啊
Seven years per hour here. Let's make it count!
這邊
This way.
差不多兩百米
About 200 meters.
引力挺大的
The gravity's punishing.
在太空飄太久了
Been floating through space too long?
地球引力的130%
One hundred and thirty percent Earth gravity.
快 快
Come on. Come on.
- 什麼都沒有 - 應該就在這裡的
- There's nothing here. - Should be right here.
如果信號是從這裡來的
If the signal's coming from here, then...
她的發射器
Her beacon.
已經是殘骸了
Wreckage.
其他的部分呢
Where's the rest?
在山那邊
Towards the mountains!
那可不是山
Those aren't mountains.
那是巨浪
They're waves.
哦 該死 該死 該死
Oh, shit. Oh, shit. Oh, shit.
Cooper 那個浪正離我們遠去
COOPER". That one's moving away from us.
我們得找到記錄儀
We need the recorder.
Brand Doyle 回到漫遊者上來
Brand, Doyle, back to the Ranger now!
沒拿到她的資料 我是不會走的
We're not leaving without her data.
馬上回來
Get back here now!
我們沒有時間了
We do not have time!
第二波浪就要來了 我們正趕上漲潮
The second wave is coming! We're in the middle of a swell.
不 我拿到了
No, I got it.
你給我馬上回到漫遊者上來
Get your ass back to the Ranger now!
Brand 馬上回來
Brand, get back here now!
不 Cooper 你走 Cooper 走吧 我趕不上了
No, Cooper, go. Cooper, go. I can't make it.
- 快走 - CASE 去救她
- Go! - CASE, go get her.
- 走啊 - 起來 起來 Brand
- Go! - Get up. Get up, Brand!
走 走 走
Go, go! Go!
- 我趕不回去了 - 你可以的 你可以的
- I'm not gonna make it! - Yes, you are. Yes, you are!
快點 CASE接到她了 快回來 Doyle
Come on, CASE has her! Get back here, Doyle!
加油
Come on!
快到艙口來
Get to the hatch!
快 快 快
Go, go! Go!
見鬼
Shit.
手動關閉艙門
Manually overriding inside hatch!
Cooper 等等
Cooper! Wait!
引擎進水了 我必須把它關了
The engines are flooded! I'm gonna have to shut her down.
天哪
Holy shit.
抓緊
Hang on!
CASE 怎麼回事
CASE, what's the problem?
進水太多 要先排水
Too waterlogged. Let it drain.
真該死
Goddamn it!
我說了 別管我 為什麼不走
I told you to leave me! Why didn't you?
我也說了 讓你趕快回來
And I told you to get your ass back here!
區別是我們其中的一個隻想著任務
The difference is one of us was thinking about the mission!
可你想的只有回家
You were thinking about getting home.
我只是想做正確的事
I was trying to do the right thing!
這話你跟Doyle說吧
Can you tell that to Doyle?
- CASE 要用多長時間 - 45分鐘到一小時
- CASE, how much time? - Forty-five to an hour.
生命的要素
The stuff of life, huh?
這得付出多大的代價
What's this gonna cost us, Brand?
很大 幾十年
A lot. Decades.
Miller是什麼情況
What happened to Miller?
從殘骸判斷
Judging by the wreckage, she was...
著陸後不久 她就被一股巨浪打碎了
...broken up by a wave soon after impact.
這麼多年 為什麼這些殘骸還在這裡
How's the wreckage stayed together after all these years, huh?
因為時間變慢了
Because of the time slippage.
按這個星球上的時間 她幾個小時前才著陸
On this planet's time, she just landed hours ago.
她可能幾分鐘前才死
She probably just died minutes ago.
Doyle收到的資料
The data Doyle received was
只是最初的狀態 在不斷重複
just the initial status echoing endlessly.
我們對此完全沒有準備
Oh, we are not prepared for this.
你們這些書呆子的生存技能和童子軍差不多
You eggheads have the survival skills of a Boy Scout troop.
我們的智慧讓大家走到了這裡
Well, we got this far on our brains.
走出了人類歷史上最遠的距離
Farther than any human in history.
可這還遠遠不夠
Well, not far enough!
現在我們被困在這裡
And now we're stuck here till
一直到地球上都沒有人可以救為止
there won't be anyone left on Earth to save.
我也在爭分奪秒 跟你一樣 Cooper
I'm counting every minute, same as you, Cooper.
有沒有這種可能
Is there any possibility...
我們想辦法跳進黑洞
...some kind of a way we can maybe all jump in a black hole?
奪回失去的時間
Gain back the years?
別對著我搖頭
Don't shake your head at me.
時間是相對的 懂嗎
Time is relative, okay?
既可以拉長也可以壓縮 但是
It can stretch and it can squeeze, but...
但不能倒回去 不可能
...it can't run backwards. It just can't.
唯一可以
The only thing that can
像時間一樣跨越維度的 就是引力
move across dimensions, like time, is gravity.
好吧
Okay.
那些把我們引到這裡來的生命 他們通過
The beings that led us here, they communicate...
- 引力交流 對吧 - 是的
- ...through gravity, right? - Yes.
他們能從未來對我們說話嗎
Could they be talking to us from the future?
- 也許吧 - 好的 如果他們能
- Maybe. - Okay. If they can...
他們是五維空間的生命
"They" Are beings of five dimensions.
時間可能是另一種空間的實體
To them, time might be another physical dimension.
對他們來說
To them...
過去也許就像個可以走進的峽谷
...the past might be a canyon
未來 就是可以攀爬的山
that they can climb into and the future...
但是對我們來說 是不可能的
...A mountain they can climb up. But to us, it's not, okay?
Cooper 我搞砸了 我很抱歉
Look, Cooper, I screwed up. I'm sorry.
但是你也知道相對論的
But you knew about relativity.
噢
Oh.
Brand
Brand...
我女兒才十歲
...my daughter was 10 years old.
我走之前還沒來得及教她愛因斯坦的理論
I couldn't teach her Einstein's theories before I left.
你沒告訴你女兒你要去拯救世界了嗎
Couldn't you have told her you were going to save the world?
沒有
No.
當你變成父母後 你的首要任務是
When you become a parent, one thing becomes really clear.
讓你的孩子有安全感
And that is that you want to make sure your children feel safe.
所以不能告訴一個十歲的孩子 世界末日要來了
And it rules out telling a 10-year-old that the world is ending.
Cooper
Cooper?
- 還有多久引擎準備好 CASE - 一兩分鐘
- How long for the engines, CASE? - A minute or two.
沒時間了 戴上頭盔
We don't have it. Helmets on!
Brand 來副駕駛
Brand, co-pilot, you're up.
CASE 把艙內氧氣加入主推動器
CASE, blow the cabin oxygen through the main thrusters!
- 準備點火 - 收到
- We're gonna spark it. - Roger that.
- 就位 - 釋放壓力
- Locked. - Depressurizing.
引擎啟動
Engines up!
你好 Rom
Hello, Rom.
我等了好多年了
I've waited years.
多 多少年
How--? How many years?
- 到現在 - 二十三年
- By now it must be... - Twenty-three years...
四個月零八天
...four months, eight days.
Doyle呢
Doyle?
我以為我準備好了 我精通理論
I thought I was prepared. I knew the theory.
可現實是完全不同的
Reality's different.
Miller呢
And Miller?
那裡什麼都沒有
There's nothing here for us.
你怎麼不睡覺
Why didn't you sleep?
我睡了好幾覺了
Oh, I had a couple of stretches.
我以為你們不會回來了
But I stopped believing you were coming back.
我想 把生命就這樣睡掉也太浪費了
And something seemed wrong about dreaming my life away.
我從黑洞裡學到了很多
I learned what I could from the black hole...
但是卻不能傳給你父親
...but I couldn't send anything to your father.
我們能收到資訊 卻發不出去
We've been receiving, but nothing gets out.
- 他還活著嗎 - 還活著
- ls he alive? - Oh, yeah.
- 真的 - 真的
- Yeah? - Yeah.
這些年的資訊都存著呢
We've got years of messages stored.
Cooper
Cooper.
一共有二十三年的資訊
Messages span 23 years.
從頭開始放
Play it from the beginning.
嗨 爸爸
Hey, Dad.
我只是來說句話 打個招呼
Checking in. Saying hi.
呃
Um...
我畢業了 成績第二
Finished second in school.
Carlin女士還是總給我C
Miss Kurling's still giving me C's though.
說我沒追求吧 但我覺得第二還不賴
Pulled me down, but seconds not bad.
外公來參加了畢業典禮
Grandpa attended the ceremony.
呃 噢
Um-- Oh.
還有 我遇見了一個女孩 爸
I met another girl, Dad.
我
I, uh...
我覺得就是她了
I really think this is the one.
她的名字是Lois 這就是她
Name's Lois. That's her right there.
Murphy偷了外公的車
Murphy stole Grandpa's car.
她把車撞壞了 不過她沒事
She crashed it. She's okay, though.
嗨 爸
Hey, Dad.
快看
Look at this!
你當爺爺了
You're a grandpa.
他的名字是Jesse
His name's Jesse.
我本來想叫他Coop的
I kind of wanted to call him Coop,
但是Lois說下一胎吧
but Lois says, uh, maybe next time.
Donald說他已經是曾祖父了
Donald says he's already earned the "Great" Part,
別的就算了
so we just leave it at that.
噢 乖 乖
Oh, dear. Oh, dear.
和爺爺說再見
Say "Bye-bye, Grandpa."
說爺爺再見
Bye-bye, Grandpa. Okay.
抱歉 有一陣沒留消息了
Sorry it's been a while.
只是
Just"
Jesse的那些事
...what with Jesse and all.
呃
Uh...
外公上個禮拜去世了
Grandpa died last week.
我們把他葬在農場後的荒地裡 和媽媽一起
We buried him out in the back forty next to Mom and...
還有Jesse
...Jesse.
那原本是我們給你留的位置 如果你還
Which is where we would have buried you if you'd ever...
會回來的話
...come back.
Murph來參加了葬禮
Murph was there at the funeral.
我們不常見到她 但是那次她來了
We don't see her that much, but she came for that.
你不會聽到這些的 我知道
You aren't listening to this, I know that.
所有的這些資訊
All these messages are just, like...
只是飄在無邊的黑暗中
...drifting out there in the darkness.
Lois說
Lois says that, uh...
我得放下你
...I have to let you go.
呃
And, uh...
所以
...so...
我想 我最終會釋懷的
...I guess I'm letting you go.
我不知道你在哪兒 爸
I don't know where you are, Dad...
但是我希望你享有寧靜
...but I hope that you're at peace.
再見
Goodbye.
嗨 爸
Hey, Dad.
嗨 Murph
Hey, Murph.
你這個大混蛋
You son of a bitch.
你在回信的時候我從來沒留過言
I never made one of these when you were still responding...
因為我還在為你的離開生氣
...because I was so mad at you for leaving.
但是當你失去音信的時候
And then when you went quiet, it...
我覺得都是我自作自受
...seemed like I should live with that decision. And I have.
但今天是我的生日
But today's my birthday.
這個生日很特別 因為你告訴過我
And it's a special one, because you told me...
你說你回來的時候
You once told me that when you came back,
我們也許是一樣的年紀了
we might be the same age.
今天我就到你離開時的年紀了
And today I'm the age you were when you left.
所以現在就是你應該回來的時候了
So it would be a real good time for you to come back.
我不是故意打擾你
I didn't mean to intrude.
只是我從來沒有在這裡見過你
It's just that I've never seen you in here before.
因為我沒有來過
I've never been in here before.
我總是和Amelia說話
I talk to Amelia all the time.
有幫助的
It helps.
- 我很高興你也開始這麼做了 - 我沒有 我
- I'm glad you've started. - I haven't. I--
只是有一些必須說出來的話
I just had something I needed to get out.
- 我知道他們還活著 - 我知道
- I know they're still out there. - I know.
有很多原因可以導致
There are so many reasons their
我們的資訊無法正常傳輸
communications might not be getting through.
我知道 教授
I know, professor.
我都不清楚 我更怕什麼
I'm not sure what I'm more afraid of.
他們永遠不回來
Them never coming back or...
還是回來了 發現我們失敗了
...coming back to find we've failed.
那我們成功就好了
Then let's succeed.
那麼
So...
回到第四反覆運算
...back to the fourth iteration.
我們用新的引力場試試
Let's run it through some new fields.
不是有意冒犯 教授 我們已經試了上百次了
With respect, professor, we've tried that hundreds of times.
只要一次成功就行了 Murph
It only has to work once, Murph.
他們敲擊的每顆鉚釘都有可能是子彈
Every rivet that they strike could have been a bullet.
我們做得不錯 在這邊的世界
We've done well for the world here...
不管我死前有沒有解出方程式
...whether or not we crack the equation before I kick the bucket.
- 別這麼消極 教授 - 我不怕死
- Don't be morbid, professor. - I'm not afraid of death.
我是個老物理家
I'm an old physicist.
我害怕時間
I'm afraid of time.
時間
Time.
你害怕時間
You're afraid of time.
我們一直以來試圖解出這個方程的
We've been trying to solve the equation...
前提條件是時間不變
...without changing the underlying assumption about time.
- 所以呢 - 這表示
- And? - And that means...
每一個反覆運算都只是在嘗試自我證明
...each iteration is an attempt to prove its own proof.
這是遞迴 是沒有意義的
It's recursive. It's nonsensical.
你是說我一生的努力都是
Are you calling my life's work...
無意義的嗎 Murph
...nonsense, Murph?
不 我是說你一直都
No, I'm saying that you've been trying to...
在把一隻手 不
...finish it with one arm... No,
是兩隻手綁在背後來解決問題
with both arms. --tied behind your back.
我不明白為什麼
And I don't understand why.
我是個老人 Murph
I'm an old man, Murph.
我們能另找時間談麼
Can we take this point up at another time?
我想和我女兒說說話
I want to talk to my daughter.
離開地球 走進宇宙
Stepping out into the universe...
我們就必須面對星際穿越的真實情況
...we must confront the reality of interstellar travel.
我們必須超越自己的生命範疇
We must reach far beyond our own lifespans.
我們思考時 不能把自己當做個體而是作為一個種族
We must think not as individuals but as a species.
不要溫順地走入那長夜
Do not go gentle into that good night
TARS把飛船停在了預定地點
TARS kept the Endurance right where we needed her.
但是這趟旅行比我們計畫的時間長
But the trip took years longer than we anticipated.
我們的燃料不夠去所有的星球 所以
We no longer have the fuel to visit both prospects, so...
我們必須抉擇
...we have to choose.
怎麼選
But how?
它們都很有潛力
They're both promising.
Edmunds的數據要好點
Edmunds' data is better, but Dr.
但是Mann博士的星球一直在傳信號
Mann is the one still transmitting, so...
我們沒有理由懷疑Edmund的資料不好
We've no reason to suspect Edmunds's data would have soured.
他那兒有所有支撐人體生命的元素
His world has key elements to sustain human life.
- Mann博士的也是 - Cooper 這是我的專業領域
- As does Dr. Mann's. - Cooper, this is my field.
並且
And...
我真的覺得Edmund那裡更有希望
...I really believe Edmunds' is the better prospect.
- 為什麼 - 卡岡圖亞 這就是原因
- Why? - Gargantua, that's why.
看看Miller的星球吧 碳氧化合物 有機物 都有
Look at Miller's planet. Hydrocarbons, organics, yes...
但是沒有生命 一片荒涼 在Mann的星球上我們也會面臨同樣的情況
...but no life. Sterile. We'll find the same thing on Mann's.
因為黑洞嗎
Because of the black hole?
墨菲定律 有可能發生的就一定會發生
Murphy's Law. Whatever can happen will happen.
意外是進化的第一塊積木
Accident is the first building block of evolution.
但是當你繞著黑洞的軌道 就沒有足夠的意外發生
But when you're orbiting a black hole not enough can happen.
小行星和彗星都被吞噬了
It sucks in asteroids and comets,
要不我們怎麼一個也沒遇見
other events which would otherwise reach you.
我們得走的更遠一點
We need to go further afield.
你曾經說過 Mann博士
You once said that Dr. Mann...
是我們中最棒的
...was the best of us.
他很了不起 我們在這兒就是因為他
He's remarkable. We're only here because of him.
現在他就在這裡
And yet-- Yet here he is.
在那個星球上
He's on the ground, and he's
給我們發來明確的資訊 讓我們
sending a very unambiguous message, telling us...
去他的星球
...to come to his planet.
有道理 但是Edmunds的資料前景更好
Granted, but Edmunds' data is more promising.
我們應該投票
We should vote.
好吧 要是投票的話 有件事你應該要知道
Well, if we vote, there's something you should know.
Brand
Brand?
他有權知道
He has a right to know.
那與此無關
That has nothing to do with it.
- 什麼事 - 她和Wolf Edmunds是戀人關係
- What does? - She's in love with Wolf Edmunds.
- 是真的麼 - 是的
- ls that true? - Yes.
這讓我想聽從內心的聲音
And that makes me want to follow my heart.
也許我們花了太多的時間
But maybe we've spent too
試著用理論解釋一切
long trying to figure all this outwith theory.
你是個科學家 Brand
You're a scientist, Brand.
那就聽我的
So listen to me...
愛不是我們發明的東西
...when I say that love isn't something we invented. It's...
它一直存在而且很強大
...observable, powerful.
它是有意義的
It has to mean something.
愛是有意義的 沒錯
Love has meaning, yes. Social utility,
社會效益 人際交往 繁衍後代
social bonding, child rearing...
我們愛那些逝去的人 這有什麼社會效益
We love people who have died. Where's the social utility in that?
沒有
None.
也許這有更深的意義 那些
Maybe it means something more, something we can't...
我們還無法理解的
...yet understand.
也許是一些證據 一些
Maybe it's some evidence, some...
更高維度的文明
...artifact of a higher
只是我們目前還不能感知
dimension that we can't consciously perceive.
我被牽引著穿越星河宇宙
I'm drawn across the universe
去見一個數年未見的人
to someone I haven't seen in a decade...
一個我知道可能早就死了的人
...who I know is probably dead.
愛是我們唯一能夠感知的
Love is the one thing we're capable of perceiving...
超越時空維度的事物
...that transcends dimensions of time and space.
或許我們應該相信它 即使我們還未完全理解它
Maybe we should trust that, even if we can't understand it yet.
好吧 Cooper
All right, Cooper...
我承認
...yes...
能見到Wolf的幾率即使再小也讓我激動不已
...the tiniest possibility of seeing Wolf again excites me.
但這並不意味著我錯了
That doesn't mean I'm wrong.
老實說 Amelia
Honestly, Amelia...
也許你錯了
...it might.
TARS 繪出到Mann博士星球的航線
TARS, chart a course for Dr. Mann's.
我們又要損失三分之一了
We'll lose about a third again.
但明年
But next year...
明年我會去Nelson的農場工作 把損失補上
Next year I'm gonna work Nelson's farm and we'll make it up.
Nelson怎麼了
What happened to Nelson?
Murph 你還要點蛋奶酥嗎
Murph, would you like some more souffle'?
不了 我飽了 謝謝 很好吃
Oh, no. I'm full, thanks. It was delicious.
Coop 把食物吃完
Coop, finish your fritter, please.
你要留下來過夜嗎
Will you spend the night?
你的臥室和原來一模一樣
Your room is exactly as you left it. It's ready.
我得回去了
I need to get back.
我的縫紉機在那兒 但是還有很多
My sewing machine is in there, but there's plenty--
我得回去
l need to....
那裡有太多回憶了
Too many memories.
好吧 我們有辦法解決 嘿 Coop
We might have something for that. Hey, Coop.
灰太大
The dust.
Lois 我有一個朋友
Lois, I have a friend who...
可以幫他檢查一下肺部
...could look at his lungs.
- Amelia 對不起 - 你只是客觀分析
- Amelia, I'm sorry. - You were just being objective.
除非你是想懲罰我在Miller星球上犯的錯
Unless you're punishing me for screwing up on Miller's planet.
不 這並不是私人恩怨
No, this wasn't a personal decision.
如果你錯了 就有一個很私人的決定等著你了
If you're wrong, you will have a very personal decision to make.
你是參照回航的需求計算的燃料
Your fuel calculations are based on a return journey.
如果我們去Mann的星球
Strike out on Mann's planet,
你就得決定是要回到地球
and we'll have to decide whether to return home...
還是去Edmunds星球實行B計畫
...or push on to Edmunds' with Plan B.
建立殖民地能讓我們免於種族滅絕
Starting a colony could save us from extinction.
你或許得決定是回去和你的孩子們相聚
You might have to decide between seeing your children again...
還是去創造人類的未來
...and the future of the human race.
我相信你那時一定會很客觀
I trust you'll be as objective then.
他醒過來後一直要求見你
He's been asking for you since he came to.
我們就設法聯繫了你
We were trying to reach you.
Murph
Murph.
我在這兒 教授
I'm here, professor.
我讓大家失望了
I let you all down.
不 你引領我們走了很遠了 馬上就要成功了
No, you got us so far. Real close.
我會完成你的研究
I'll finish what you started.
好 很好 Murph
Good, good Murph.
你有信念
You had faith...
這麼多
...all those...
這麼多年來
...all those years.
我
I...
我要你堅守信念
I asked you to have faith.
我想要你相信
I wanted you to believe...
你父親
...that your father...
一定會回來
...would come back.
教授 我相信
I do, professor.
原諒我 Murph
Forgive me, Murph.
沒有什麼需要原諒的
There's nothing to forgive.
我
I.
我說謊了 Murph
I lied, Murph.
我騙了你
I lied to you.
他根本沒必要
There was no need for him to...
再回來
To come back.
我們沒有希望了
There is no way to help us.
但是A計畫呢
But Plan A...
所有的這一切呢 所有的這些人
All this. All these people.
還有這個方程
And the equation.
我父親知道嗎
Did my father know?
是他拋棄了我嗎
Did he leave me?
不要
Do...
溫順
...not...
地
...go...
走進
...gentle...
不
No.
不要
No!
你不能走
You can't leave.
你 不
You-- No.
Brand博士 我很遺憾地
Dr. Brand, I'm sorry to
告訴你 你父親今天去世了 他走的時候很平和
tell you that your father died today. He had no pain.
沒有遭受一絲痛苦
He was at peace.
我很遺憾 請你節哀
I'm very sorry for your loss.
Brand 你知道嗎
Brand, did you know?
他早就告訴你了吧
He told you, right?
你知道的
You knew.
這一切都是騙局
This was all a sham.
你們把我們扔在這兒
You left us here.
任我們窒息
To suffocate.
餓死
To starve.
是凍雲
Frozen cloud.
曼恩博士
沒事了
It's okay.
都過去了
希望你永遠都不會知道
Pray you never learn...
再次見到人類有多美好
...just how good it can be to see another face.
開始的時候我沒報多大希望
I hadn't a lot of hope to begin with, but...
過了很久 更是希望全無
...after so long, I had none.
我的補給品全部用完了
My supplies were completely exhausted.
最後一次休眠 我甚至都沒設置喚醒日期
The last time I went to sleep, I didn't even set a waking date.
你們真正地讓我起死回生了
You have literally raised me from the dead.
- 拉撒路 - 嗯
- Lazarus. - Hm.
- 其他人呢 - 恐怕就剩你了
- What about the others? - l'm afraid you're it, sir.
你是說到目前為止 當然了
So far, surely.
不 以我們現在的狀況
No, our present situation is that
幾乎不可能援救其他人了
there's very little chance of rescuing any others.
Mann博士 Mann博士
Dr. Mann. Dr. Mann?
跟我們說說你的星球
Tell us about your world.
希望是我們的星球
Our world, we hope.
我們的星球很冷
Our world, uh, is cold...
荒涼
...stark...
但不可否認它也很美
...but undeniably beautiful.
白天有67個小時 很冷
The days are 67 hours long, cold.
夜晚是
The nights are...
更冷的67個小時
...67 far colder hours.
引力只有地球的百分之八十 很舒服
The gravity is a very, very pleasant 80 percent of the Earth's.
這裡 我登陸的地方 水質是鹼性的
Now, up here where I landed, the water is alkali...
空氣裡氨氣的比重很大
...and the air has too much ammonia
呼吸幾分鐘就受不了了
to breathe for more than just a few minutes...
但是 在它的表層下面還有一層
...but down at the surface, and there is a surface...
在這層 氯氣開始消散
...the chlorine dissipates.
氨氣也轉化成
The ammonia gives way to
結晶性烴和可供有機體呼吸
crystalline hydrocarbons and breathable air.
的空氣
To organics.
也許甚至可供生命體呼吸
Possibly even to life.
我們也許能共用這個星球
We might be sharing this world.
這些是表層的讀數嗎
These readings are from the surface?
這些年 我放了很多探測器
Over the years, I've dropped various probes.
你勘探了多遠
How far have you explored?
我設法進行了幾次主要的遠征探險
l've mounted several major expeditions.
但是由於氧氣有限
But with oxygen in limited supply,
大部分跑腿的工作都是KIPP完成的
KIPP there really did most of the legwork.
- 它怎麼了 - 性能老化
- What went wrong with him, sir? - Degeneration.
它將我們發現的第一個有機體誤當成了氨結晶
He misidentified the first organics we found as ammonia crystals.
我們掙扎了一段時間
We struggled on for a time,
最終我還是讓它退役了
but ultimately I decommissioned him and...
然後用他的電源來使任務繼續下去
...used his power source to keep the mission going.
關掉它之前 我以為自己真的要孤身一人了
I thought I was alone before I shut him down.
您能讓我檢查一下它嗎
Would you like me to look at him?
不 不 它需要的是人類
No. No. He needs a human touch.
Brand博士 CASE從空間站
Dr. Brand, CASE is relaying
給您傳來一個消息
a message for you from the comm station.
好的 我馬上就來 不好意思
Okay. Be right there. Excuse me.
Brand博士 我很遺憾地告訴你 你父親今天去世了
Dr. Brand, I'm sorry to tell you that your father died today.
他走的時候很平和 沒有遭受一絲痛苦
He had no pain. He was at peace.
我為你的損失感到遺憾
I'm sorry for your loss.
那是Murph嗎
ls that Murph?
她 她長大了
She's... She's grown.
你知道嗎 Brand
Brand, did you know?
他早就告訴你了吧
He told you, right?
你知道的
You knew.
這一切都是騙局
This was all a sham.
你們把我們扔在這兒
You left us here.
任我們窒息
To suffocate.
餓死
To starve.
我父親也知道嗎
Did my father know too?
爸爸
Dad?
我就是想知道
I just want to know...
你是把我扔在這兒等死嗎
...if you left me here to die.
我只想知道真相
I just have to know.
Cooper 我
Cooper, my...
我父親將畢生精力
My father dedicated...
獻給了A計畫
...his whole life to Plan A.
我完全不知道她在說什麼
I have no idea what she's talking about.
我知道
I do.
他 他難道從未想過要把人類送出地球嗎
He never even hoped to get the people off the Earth?
沒有
No.
但他花了四十年的時間研究如何解引力方程式
But he's been trying to solve the gravity equation for 40 years.
Amelia 在我離開之前 你父親就已經解出這個方程了
Amelia, your father solved his equation before I even left.
那他為什麼不用呢
Then why wouldn't he use it?
因為這個方程不能調和
The equation couldn't reconcile
相對論和量子力學 你還需要更多
relativity with quantum mechanics. You need more.
更多 更多的什麼
More? More what?
更多的資料 你得探進黑洞
More data. You need to see into a black hole.
自然法則禁止了裸奇點
The laws of nature prohibit a naked singularity.
Romilly 那是真的嗎
Romilly, is that true?
假設黑洞是個牡蠣
If a black hole is an oyster,
那奇點就是裡面的珍珠了
then the singularity's the pearl inside.
由於引力太大 導致它一直深藏在黑暗裡
The gravity's so strong, it's always hidden in darkness...
在邊界之內
...behind the horizon.
所以我們稱它為黑洞
That's why we call it a black hole.
好吧 那如果我們能看到邊界之外呢
Okay, but if we see beyond the horizon...
不可能的 Coop
We can't, Coop.
有些事本不應該說出來的
There are some things that aren't meant to be known.
你父親找到了另一個方法
Your father had to find another
能使人類免於滅絕
way to save the human race from extinction.
就是B計畫 殖民地
Plan B. A colony.
為什麼不說出來
Why not tell people?
為什麼還要建那些空間站
Why keep building those stations?
因為他知道這有多難
He knew how hard it would be...
要讓人們齊心協力
...to get people to work
去延續人類這一種群 而非拯救他們自己
together to save the species instead of themselves.
或是他們的孩子
Or their children.
胡說
Bullshit.
要不是你相信這樣做能救你的孩子 你絕對不會來這裡的
You never would've come unless you believed you would save them.
人類的進化還沒能超越那個簡單的障礙
Evolution has yet to transcend that simple barrier.
我們可以深沉而無私地
We can care deeply, selflessly about...
關心自己的親人 但是
...those we know, but that
對於那些不認識的人 我們少有付出
empathy rarely extends beyond our line of sight.
但那個謊言
But the lie.
那個彌天大謊
That monstrous lie?
是不可原諒的
Unforgivable.
他知道
And he knew that.
他早就準備好了
He was prepared to destroy
為了拯救整個種群 甘願放棄自己的人性
his own humanity in order to save the species.
- 他做出了極大的犧牲 - 不
- He made an incredible sacrifice. - No.
做出極大犧牲的
An incredible sacrifice is being
是那些在地球上等死的人
made by the people on Earth who are gonna die!
因為他那該死的自負
Because in his fucking arrogance...
他將那些人判了死刑
...he declared their case hopeless.
我很抱歉 Cooper
I'm sorry, Cooper...
他們的確毫無希望
...their case is hopeless.
不 不是
No. No.
我們才是人類的未來
We are the future.
Cooper 我能做點什麼
Cooper, what can I do?
讓我回家
Let me go home.
你真的能確定嗎
You're absolutely positive?
他的演算法沒錯 他好多年前就解出來了
His solution was correct. He'd had it for years.
- 那沒用嗎 - 那只是一半的答案
- It's worthless? - It's half the answer.
好吧 那你怎麼找到另一半
Okay, how do you find the other half?
在外太空 從黑洞裡找
Out there? A black hole.
- 但是在地球上 - 怎麼
- But stuck down here on Earth? - Yeah?
就沒法找到了
I'm not sure you can.
天啊 他們都在收拾離開
God, they just pack up and leave.
他們能撤離去哪兒呢
What are they hoping to find?
生存
Survival.
該死
Damn it.
Murph 難道 難道人們就沒權利知道嗎
Murph, don't--? Don't people have a right to know?
恐慌無濟於事 我們只要繼續工作 像往常一樣
Panic won't help. We just have to keep working, same as ever.
但那不正是
But isn't that exactly what
Brand教授一直以來對我們的操縱嗎
Professor Brand was manipulating us to do?
Brand放棄了我們 但是我仍在嘗試解決
Brand gave up on us. I'm still trying to solve this.
那
So...
你有主意了嗎
...do you have an idea?
只是一種感覺
A feeling.
我跟你講過我的幽靈
I told you about my ghost.
我爸爸以為我稱它為幽靈
My dad thought I called it a ghost...
是因為我怕它
...because I was scared of it.
但是我從來沒害怕過它
But I was never scared of it.
我稱它為幽靈是因為 我覺得
I called it a ghost because it felt...
它很像一個人
It felt like a person.
它一直在試圖告訴我些什麼
It was trying to tell me something.
如果地球上有解 一定藏在那裡
If there's an answer here on Earth, it's back there...
在那間屋子裡
...somehow, in that room.
所以我必須找到它
So I have to find it.
我們快沒時間了
We're running out of time.
那些備用的氧氣淨化器呢
What about auxiliary oxygen scrubbers?
不 可以留下來 反正大部分的路程裡我都會休眠
No, they can stay. I'll be sleeping anyway.
- 嘿 Coop - 怎麼了
- Hey, Coop? - Yeah?
對於你的返程旅行我有個建議
I have a suggestion for your return journey.
- 好吧 什麼建議 - 最後一次嘗試一下黑洞
- Yeah, what's that? - Have one last crack at the black hole.
我要回家了 Rom
I'm going home, Rom.
是的 我知道 這又不花時間
Yeah, I know. This isn't going to cost you any time.
對地球上的人也是一個機會
There's a chance for the people on Earth.
- 跟我說說 - 卡岡圖亞是個很古老的旋轉黑洞
- Talk to me. - Gargantua's an older spinning black hole.
- 就是我們所說的溫和奇點 - 溫和嗎
- It's what we call a gentle singularity. - Gentle?
並不溫和 但是引力潮汐來得很快
They're hardly gentle. But the tidal gravity is so quick that...
如果穿越的速度夠快
...something crossing the
或許能逃過一劫 比如探測器
horizon fast might survive. A probe, say.
穿越後會怎樣
What happens after it crosses?
邊界另一邊是什麼樣 我們完全沒有概念
After the horizon is a complete mystery.
所以倒不如問 假如探測器看到了奇點
So, what's to say there isn't some way that the probe...
但是沒辦法把量子數據傳遞出來 該怎麼辦
...can glimpse the singularity and relay the quantum data?
如果他配備了所需的裝置 可以發射任何一種脈衝能量
If he's equipped to transmit every form of energy that can pulse.
教授 什麼時候這個探測器成了"他"了
Just when did this probe become a "He," Professor?
很明顯TARS就是一個候選
TARS is the obvious candidate.
我已經告訴他該怎麼做了
I've already told him what to look for.
我需要KIPP身上的舊光學發射器 Cooper
I'd need the old optical transmitter off KIPP, Cooper.
你要替我們去
You'd do this for us?
在你熱淚盈眶前
Before you get all teary,
先試著提醒自己 作為機器人 我必須遵守你的任何指令
remember that as a robot I have to do anything you say.
你的指示燈壞了
Your cue light's broken.
我不是在開玩笑
I'm not joking.
我需要TARS從KIPP身上取點零件安上
I'll need TARS to remove and adapt some components from KIPP.
好吧 但不要損壞他的資訊管理系統
I don't want to disturb his archival functions.
我會看著他的
I'll supervise.
好的
All right.
Mann博士 我們得找三個安全基地
Dr. Mann, we need to find three secure sites.
一個用作Brand的實驗室 另外兩個用做棲居地
One for Brand's lab, two for habitat.
一旦那些飛船著陸後 就不好再做移動了
Once those modules have landed, you don't want to move them.
好吧 我可以帶你去那些探測地點 但我覺得
I can take you to the probe sites, but I don't think...
那裡的條件可能不穩定 我想我們應該再等等
...these conditions will hold. I think we should wait.
CASE已經帶著剩下的蒸餾淨水器過來了
CASE is headed down with the rest of the distillery equipment.
我希望在天黑之前把營地建好
I'd really like to secure those sites by nightfall.
好吧 指不定什麼時候就刮暴風了
Well, these squalls do usually blow over.
沒問題
Okay, then.
- 你得有遠距離傳輸器 - 有呢
- You'll need a long-range transmitter. - Got it.
- 充滿電了嗎 - 是的
- Are you charged? - Yeah.
跟我來
Follow me.
TARS 72個小時 記住了
TARS, 72 hours, yeah?
收到 明白 Cooper
Roger that, Cooper.
Brand告訴了我你為什麼得回去
Brand told me why you feel you have to go back.
但是出於職責 我還是想說
But I'd be remiss if I didn't at least mention...
像咱們這樣的任務
...that a mission such as
多一個工程師 就多了一份保障
ours could certainly use an extra engineer.
你最好開慢點 小子 安全第一 CASE 記住
You better slow down, turbo. Safety first, CASE, remember.
安全第一 Cooper
Safety first, Cooper.
Mann博士 我想告訴你我真的很榮幸能參與其中
I have to tell you, Dr. Mann, I'm honored to be a part of this.
但是一旦咱們建好了營地
But once we set up base camp
確保飛船安全 我的任務就完成了
and secure those modules, my work's done here.
我就要回家了
I'm going home.
你心中有牽掛 但即使沒有家庭
You have attachments. But even without a family...
我敢保證
...I can promise you that that
那種對陪伴的渴望也會很強烈
yearning to be with other people is powerful.
正是那種根生蒂固的情感
That emotion is at the foundation...
讓我們之所以為人 這並不易被掠去
...of what makes us human. It's not to be taken lightly.
- 你咳了多久了 - 有一段時間了
- How long have you had that cough? - A while.
媽媽讓我在這兒玩
Mom lets me play in here.
我不會亂碰你的東西
I don't touch your stuff.
墨菲的收納盒
動作最好輕點
Just take this gently.
你知道為什麼我們
You know why we couldn't
不直接派機器來完成這些任務嗎
just send machines on these missions, don't you?
因為機器不能隨機應變
A machine doesn't improvise
因為你不能把對死亡的恐懼設置到他們的程式裡
well because you can't program a fear of death.
我們的生存本能往往使我們
Our survival instinct is our single greatest...
絕處逢生 以你為例
...source of inspiration. Take you, for example.
作為父親
A father...
你的生存渴望延伸到你的孩子身上
...with a survival instinct that extends to your kids.
你知道根據科學研究
What does research tell us is
人在臨死前看到的最後畫面是什麼嗎
the last thing you're going to see before you die?
是孩子 是他們的臉
Your children. Their faces.
在死亡的瞬間 你的意識會更強烈地
At the moment of death, your mind's gonna push...
刺激你掙扎求生
...A little bit harder to survive.
為了他們
For them.
深呼吸
Deep breath.
嘿 我猜你是Coop
Uh, hey. I bet you're Coop.
你能坐這兒等一會兒嗎
Why don't you have a seat here for me?
很糟糕 他們得離開這兒
It's bad. They cannot stay here.
- 明白嗎 - 好的
- Okay? - Yeah.
TARS 怎麼這麼久
TARS, what's taking so long?
教授 我遇到了點麻煩 沒法兒完成初始化
Professor, I am having trouble completing the boot up.
我不明白
I don't understand.
這挺可笑的
It's funny.
當我離開地球的時候
When I left Earth...
我覺得自己已經做好了死的準備
...I thought I was prepared to die.
但事實是
The truth is...
我從沒認真考慮過
...I never really considered
我的星球不適合居住的可能性
the possibility that my planet wasn't the one.
結果和當初的預想完全不同
Nothing worked out the way it was supposed to.
咱們走吧
Let's go.
嘿 小朋友 我們現在做個深呼吸
All right, buddy, give me a big deep breath.
什麼情況
What is this?
- 你在幹什麼 - 對不起
- What are you doing? - I'm sorry!
我不能讓你開走那艘飛船
I can't let you leave with that ship.
我需要它來完成這個計畫
We're gonna need it to complete the mission...
一旦其他人意識到這個星球並不像我說的那樣
...once the others realize what this place isn't.
我們都活不了 對不起
We cannot survive here. I'm sorry!
我很抱歉
I'm sorry!
他們不能再待在這兒了 你得趕緊離開
They can't stay here anymore. You have to leave right now.
讓我把事情挑明瞭吧
Let me make something abundantly clear.
你肩負著責任呢
You have a responsibility--
- 該死 - Coop 幫她拿行李 她要回去了
- Oh! Jesus! - Coop, get her stuff. She's going home.
爸爸可沒把你養成現在這副蠢樣 Tom
Dad didn't raise you to be this dumb, Tom!
養我的可不是爸爸 是外公
Dad didn't raise me, Grandpa did.
他就在後面 埋在媽媽和Jesse旁邊
And he's buried out back with Mom and Jesse.
所有的資料都是你編的嗎
You faked all the data?
是的
Yeah.
根本就沒有含氧氣的地下層嗎
There's no surface?
沒有
No.
我也試過盡職盡責
I tried to do my duty, Cooper...
但我第一天到這裡的時候
...but I knew the day that
就知道這個地方毫無希望
I arrived here that this place had nothing.
在好幾年裡 我努力克制
And I resisted the temptation for years...
但是我也知道
...but I knew that...
只需按下那個按鈕
...if I just pressed that button, then...
就一定會有人來救我
...somebody would come and save me.
你這個該死的懦夫
You fucking coward.
是啊
Yes.
聽著 如果你不想走
Listen, if you're not going to go,
那就讓你的家人走 放他們一條生路
let your family go. Just save your family.
然後和你去地下生活嗎
And we go live underground with you?
和你一起祈禱爸爸回來救咱們嗎
Pray that Daddy comes to save us?
爸爸不會回來了 他根本就沒打算回來 現在這一切都得靠我
Dad's not coming back. He never was coming back. It's up to me.
你能拯救每個人嗎
You're gonna save everybody?
- 就因為爸爸不能嗎 - 爸爸根本就沒試過
- Because Dad couldn't do it. - Dad didn't even try!
他拋棄了我們
Dad just abandoned us!
他把我們留在這兒等死
He left us here to die.
他們不會跟你走的
Nobody's going with you.
那你就等著再失去一個孩子吧
You gonna wait for your next kid to die?
滾出去
Get out.
別再回來了
And don't come back.
那些都留給你了
You can keep my stuff.
停手
Stop it!
不 不
No. No!
Mann博士 你有百分之五十的幾率會弄死你自己
Dr. Mann, there's a 50-50 chance you're gonna kill yourself!
這是我這些年裡遇到的最好的幾率了
Those are the best odds I've had in years.
別指責我 Cooper
Don't judge me, Cooper.
你從沒經受過我這樣的考驗
You were never tested like I was.
沒人體驗過
Few men have been.
你已經盡力了 Murph
You tried your best, Murph.
你感覺到了 對嗎
You're feeling it, aren't you?
求生的本能
The survival instinct.
正是它一直驅使著我 它驅使著每個人
That's what drove me. It's what drives all of us.
它也將拯救我們
And it's what's gonna save us.
因為我想救所有的人 為了你 Cooper
Because I want to save all of us. For you, Cooper.
對不起 我不能 我不能看著你遭受這一切 對不起
I'm sorry, I can't watch you go through this. I'm sorry.
我以為我可以 但是我不行
I thought I could, but I can't.
我在這兒陪著你
I'm here. I'm here for you.
聽著我的聲音 Cooper 我在這兒
Just listen to my voice, Cooper.
我在這兒
I'm right here.
你不是一個人
You're not alone.
你看見你的孩子們了嗎
Do you see your children?
沒事的
It's okay.
他們在那兒等著你呢
They are right there with you.
出發前Brand教授給你讀那首詩了嗎
Did Professor Brand tell you that poem before you left?
你還記得嗎
Do you remember?
不要溫順地走入那長夜
Do not go gentle into that good night
白日將盡
Old age should burn and rave
暮年仍應燃燒咆哮
At close of day
怒斥吧 怒斥那光明漸逝
Rage, rage against the dying of the light
Brand 救命
Brand! Help!
- 救命 - Cooper
- Help! - Cooper?
CASE
CASE!
沒有空氣
No air.
氨氣
Ammonia.
Cooper Cooper 我馬上就來 CASE
Cooper. Cooper, we're coming! CASE!
- 我得到座標了 - 快 快 快
- I have a fix. - Go! Go, go, go!
出發
And away!
Cooper 我們來了 堅持住 不要說話
Cooper, we're coming. Hang in there. Don't talk.
儘量減少呼吸 我們馬上就到了
Try to breathe as little as possible. We're almost there.
這有安全密碼鎖
There's a security lockout, sir.
需要人類才能訪問
It requires a person to access function.
交給你了 先生
It's all yours, sir.
屏住呼吸
Try not to breathe.
我們來了 馬上就到了
We're coming. We're coming right now.
CASE 快點 快點
CASE, come on! Come on!
我們要開快點 快點快點 再快一點
We got to go faster, CASE! Faster, faster, faster!
堅持住 加油啊
Hang in there. Come on.
我看見他了 看見他了 傾斜 右斜
I see him, I see him! CASE, bank! Bank right!
Cooper Cooper
Cooper! Cooper!
我來了
I'm here!
訪問存檔
這些資料根本講不通啊
This data makes no sense.
對不起
I'm sorry.
- 什麼 - Mann在撒謊
- What? - Mann was lying!
走 走
Go. Go.
Romilly
Romilly.
Romilly!
你聽得到嗎 Romilly
Romilly! Do you read me, Romilly?
當心 教授 當心
Step back, professor! Step back!
Romilly 你聽得到嗎
Romilly... Romilly, do you read me?
你留下看車
Keep watch!
Lois
Lois?
- 你為什麼不小心一點 CASE - 安全第一 Cooper
- What happened to caution, CASE? - Safety first, Cooper.
Romilly Romilly 聽得到嗎 我是Brand
Romilly? Romilly, do you read me? This is Brand.
Romilly
Romilly?
Brand博士 Cooper 剛才發生了爆炸
Dr. Brand. Cooper. There's been an explosion.
在Mann博士的營地
Dr. Mann's compound.
TARS TARS 十點鐘方向
TARS, TARS, 10 o'clock!
TARS上來以後告訴我
Let me know when TARS is aboard.
Romilly沒能倖存
Romilly did not survive.
我沒能救下他
I could not save him.
- TARS上來了 - 那就讓我來飛
- TARS is in. - I'll take her now.
- 能看到漫遊者嗎 - 他在駛向軌道
- Do we have a fix on the Ranger? - He's pushing into orbit!
如果他控制了那個飛船我們就死定了
If he takes control of that ship, we're dead.
- 他是想丟下我們嗎 - 他已經動手了
- He'd maroon us? - He is marooning us.
快下樓 在車旁邊等著
I'll meet you guys downstairs. Go wait by the car.
快來 把你的包給我
Come on! Give me your bag.
坐到後排去 馬上坐到後排去
Get in the backseat. Get in the backseat now!
Mann博士 請回復
Dr. Mann, please respond.
Dr. Mann, please respond!
他不知道永恆號的對接步驟
He doesn't know the Endurance docking procedure.
- 可是自動駕駛儀知道啊 - TARS已經把它關了
- The autopilot does. - Not since TARS disabled it.
太好了
Nice.
- TARS 你的信任度設置是多少 - 顯然比你的低
- What's your trust setting, TARS? - Lower than yours apparently.
不要嘗試對接
Do not attempt docking.
再說一遍 不要嘗試對接
I repeat, do not attempt docking.
請回
Please res--
自動對接程式無回應
Auto-docking sequence withheld.
- 忽略 - 您無此許可權
- Override. - Unauthorized.
忽略
Override.
您無此許可權
Unauthorized.
不要嘗試對接 重複一遍
Do not attempt docking. I repeat,
不要嘗試對接 請回
do not attempt docking. Please resp--
慢慢向永恆號靠近
Moving slowly toward the Endurance.
對接不完全
Imperfect contact.
- 忽略 - 艙門已鎖定
- Override. - Hatch lockout.
- 他對接上了嗎 - 還沒全對上
- ls he locked on yet? - imperfectly.
Mann博士 不要
Dr. Mann, do not--
艙門鎖定已解除
Hatch lockout disengaged.
Mann博士 再重複一遍 不要打開艙門
Dr. Mann, do not, I repeat, do not open the hatch.
再重複一遍 不要打開艙門
I repeat, do not open the hatch.
如果艙門打開了 氣密艙會失去壓力
If you open the hatch, the airlock will depressurize.
- 如果他強行打開會怎樣 - 沒好事
- What happens if he blows the airlock? - Nothing good.
好 往後退 快往後退 CASE 馬上後退
Okay, pull back. Retro thrusters, everything we've got, CASE!
- 已經全速後退 - 往後退
- Thrusters are full! - Back!
CASE 讓我連接到機艙的電腦
CASE, Relay my transmission to the onboard computer...
並將我的話以緊急廣播的形式重複播送
...and have it rebroadcast as emergency P.A.
Mann博士
Dr. Mann--
重複一遍 不要打開內艙門 重複一遍
I repeat, do not open the inner hatch. I repeat--
Brand嗎
Brand?
不管他是怎麼跟你說的
I don't know what he said to you...
現在我要掌控永恆號了
...but I am taking command of the Endurance.
然後我們再談完成任務的事情
And then we can talk about completing the mission.
Mann博士 聽我說
Dr. Mann, listen to me.
這不是關於我的性命
This is not about my life.
或是Cooper的性命 而是全人類的性命
Or Cooper's life. This is about all mankind.
總有一天
There is a moment--
這不
lt is not sa--
噢 天哪
Oh, my God.
Cooper 不要再把燃料
Cooper, there's no point using
- 浪費在追逐上 - 給我分析永恆號的旋轉情況
- fuel to chase-- - Analyze the Endurance's spin.
- Cooper 你在幹什麼 - 對接
- Cooper, what are you doing? -Docking.
永恆號的轉速是每分鐘67 68轉
Endurance rotation is 67, 68 RPM.
好 準備好用反向推進器和它同步旋轉
Okay, get ready to match our spin with the retro thrusters.
- 你不可能做到的 - 不
- It's not possible. - No...
我必須做到
...it's necessary.
永恆號已經進入平流層
Endurance is hitting stratosphere!
永恆號沒有隔熱板
She's got no heat shield.
- CASE 準備好了嗎 - 準備好了
- CASE, you ready? - Ready.
Cooper 沒時間安全第一了
Cooper! This is no time for caution.
CASE 我要是暈過去了 就由你來接管
CASE, if I black out, you take the stick.
TARS 準備啟動對接裝置
TARS, get ready to engage the docking mechanism.
永恆號已經開始升溫了
Endurance is starting to heat.
還有20尺
Twenty feet out.
向右舷傾斜3度 Cooper
I need three degrees starboard, Cooper.
還有10尺
Ten feet out.
Cooper 我們已經對齊了
Cooper, we are lined up.
開始旋轉
Initiating spin!
加油 TARS
Come on, TARS.
Come on, TARS!
- Cooper 我們對接成功了 - 降低速度
- We are locked, Cooper. - Locked. Easing up!
慢點
Easy.
反向推進器
Retro thrusters!
啟動主引擎
Main engines on.
飛船已經離開軌道了 來吧 寶貝
Pushing out of orbit. Come on, baby.
關閉主引擎
Killing main engines!
好了 我們已經離開軌道了
Okay, we're out of orbit.
好了 請期待下一個表演項目
Okay. And for our next trick!
最好別演砸了 我們正進入卡岡圖亞的引力範圍
It'll have to be good. We're heading into Gargantua's pull.
哦 糟糕
Oh, shit.
- CASE 你來操作 - 好的
- CASE, take the stick. - Roger that.
Cooper 我們正在向卡岡圖亞滑去
Cooper, we're slipping towards Gargantua.
我是否該開啟主引擎
Shall I use main engines?
不
No.
我們要讓飛船儘量保持滑行
We got to let her slide as far as we can.
- 說吧 - Cooper 我有好消息也有壞消息
- Give it to me. - There's good news, there's bad news.
這話我聽過了 TARS 有話直說吧
Yeah, I've heard that one, TARS. Give it to me straight.
備用發電機已經啟動
The backup generator kicked in,
系統可以穩定運行了 一切順利
so the system's stable. They're all good.
太好了
Good.
好了 導航器已經被完全摧毀了
Okay. The navigational hub has been completely destroyed.
我們的物資已經不夠我們回到地球了
We don't have enough life support to make it back to Earth...
但我覺得我們可以撐到Edmunds的星球
...but we can scratch our way to Edmunds' planet.
燃料怎麼辦
What about fuel?
不夠 但我有個計畫
Not enough. But I have a plan.
讓卡岡圖亞把我們拉向它的邊界
We let Gargantua pull us down close to her horizon.
用引力彈弓效應
Then a powered slingshot around,
把我們射向Edmunds的星球
launching us towards Edmunds' planet.
- 手動操作嗎 - 這就是選我的原因
- Manually? - That's what I'm here for.
我會讓咱們準確地駛入臨界軌道
I'm gonna take us just inside the critical orbit.
- 那時間畸變呢 - 現在不是考慮
- What about time slippage? - Neither of us has time to worry...
相對論的時候 Brand博士
...about relativity right now, Dr. Brand.
抱歉 Cooper
I'm sorry, Cooper.
只要我們在卡岡圖亞周圍獲得了足夠的速度
Once we've gathered enough speed around Gargantua...
我們就把登陸艙1號
...we use Lander 1...
將我們推離黑洞的引力
...push us out of the black hole's gravity.
登陸艙的聯動裝置已經被毀了
The Lander's linkages have been destroyed...
所以我們必須要手動操作它
...so we'll have to control manually.
一旦登陸艙一號的燃料耗盡 TARS就會操作分離
Once Lander 1 is spent, TARS will detach--
然後被黑洞一下子吸進去
And get sucked into that black hole.
為什麼非要讓TARS分離
Why does TARS have to detach?
我們不得不甩掉一些重量 才能擺脫引力
We have to shed the weight to escape the gravity.
牛頓第三定律
Newton's third law.
人類所知道的 到達一個地方的唯一方法
The only way humans have ever figured out of getting somewhere...
就是拋棄一些東西
...is to leave something behind.
Cooper 你不能要求TARS這麼做
Cooper, you can't ask TARS to do this for us.
他是個機器人 所以你不需要刻意要求他
He's a robot. So you don't have to ask him to do anything.
Cooper 你個混蛋
Cooper, you asshole!
抱歉 要讓你受委屈了
Sorry, you broke up a little bit there.
這就是我們的使命 Brand博士
It's what we intended, Dr. Brand.
這是我們拯救地球上的人類的唯一機會
It's our only chance to save people on Earth.
如果我能想辦法
If I can find a way to
把那兒的量子資料傳輸出去
transmit the quantum data I'll find in there...
那他們說不定還能活下去
...they might still make it.
但願還有人能撐到那個時候
Let's just hope there's still someone there to save.
已達到最大速度
Maximum velocity achieved.
準備加速脫離軌道
Prepare to fire escape thrusters.
準備好了嗎
Ready?
準備完畢
Ready.
主引擎點火倒計時 三
Main engine ignition in three...
二
...two...
一 啟動
...one. Mark.
加油啊 寶貝兒
Come on, baby.
登陸艙1號 聽我指示
Lander 1 engines, on my mark.
三
Three...
二
...two...
一 啟動
...one. Mark.
漫遊者2號引擎 聽我指示
Ranger 2 engines, on my mark.
三 二 一
Three, two, one...
- 啟動 - 點火
- Mark. - Fire!
這點小事花了我們五十一年
This little maneuver's gonna cost us 51 years!
你聽著也不像快一百二的人啊
You don't sound so bad for pushing 120!
一號登陸艙 燃料即將耗盡
登陸艙1號 準備分離 聽我指揮
Lander 1, prepare to detach on my mark.
三 二
Three, two...
一 開始
...one. Mark.
分離
Detach!
- 再見了 TARS - 再見 Brand博士
- Goodbye, TARS. - Goodbye, Dr. Brand.
- 那頭見啦 Coop - 那頭見啦 小子
- See you on the other side, Coop. - See you there, Slick!
徘徊者二號 燃料即將耗盡
不錯 CASE
Okay, CASE.
- 飛得有驚無險 - 還不是師父教導有方
- Nice reckless flying! - Learned from the master.
- 漫遊者2號 準備分離 - 什麼
- Ranger 2, prepare to detach. - What?
不 不 Cooper Cooper你在幹什麼
No! No! Cooper! What are you doing?
牛頓第三定律 你總得扔下點什麼
Newton's third law. You got to leave something behind.
你明明說了這些資源夠兩個人用
You told me we had enough resources for both of us.
我們說好的 Amelia
We agreed, Amelia...
90%誠實
...90 percent.
不要
Don't.
分離
Detach.
好了 我們正在俯衝
Okay, I am nosing down.
即將到達黑洞邊界
Approaching the event horizon.
左舷已經接觸到邊界
Portside, dipping down beneath it...
馬上就要穿過去了
...to go through it.
正在靠近黑暗
Heading towards blackness.
我能看見一點
I have a visual of the event.
一片黑暗
It's all black.
TARS 聽得到嗎
TARS, do you read me?
周圍全是黑的
It's all blackness.
TARS 你聽得見嗎 完畢
TARS! Do you read me? Over.
好吧
Okay.
螢幕
Screens...
開始受到干擾
...getting interference.
控制杆已經失靈 這裡有閃光
Losing control of the stick. I got flashes.
黑暗中有白色閃光
Flashes of lightness and blackness.
引力開始波動 波動幅度變大
The turbulence in the gravity is increasing.
啊
Ah.
電腦已經癱瘓
The computers are going down. Agh.
是引力的作用 操縱杆已經失靈了
Gravitational pull. I'm losing control of the stick.
Murph Murph 快走吧
Murph? Murph, come on!
彈出 彈出
Eject. Eject.
彈出
Eject.
Murph
Murph.
Murph Murph Murph
Murph! Murph! Murph!
Murphy
不 不 不
No, no, no!
Murphy
不 不
No! No!
你要走的話就走吧
If you're leaving, just go.
不 不 不
No, no. No.
不 別走 別走啊 你個蠢貨
No, don't go. Don't go, you idiot.
不要走
Don't go!
摩爾斯電碼 摩爾斯電碼
Morse. Morse.
摩爾斯電碼
Morse.
點 點
Dot. Dot.
"s"
"t"
"a"
橫
Dash!
橫 橫
Dash! Dash!
Murph
Murph!
Murph 不要浪費時間了 快走
Murph, we don't have time for this! Come on!
"Y"
Y.
"留下"
"Stay!"
快點 快點 Murph 快點
Come on. Come on, Murph. Come on!
它說了什麼 它說了什麼 Murph
What's it say? What's it say, Murph?
它說了什麼
What's it say?
"留下"
"Stay.
告訴他 Murph
Tell him, Murph.
讓他留下來
Make him stay.
讓他留下來 Murph
Make him stay, Murph.
留下
讓他留下來 Murph
Make him stay, Murph.
別讓我走 Murph
Don't let me leave, Murph!
不要讓我走啊 Murph
不 不 不
No!No!No!
那是你
It was you.
你就是我的幽靈
You were my ghost.
Cooper Cooper 聽得見嗎 Cooper
Cooper. Cooper. Come in, Cooper.
- TARS - 收到
- TARS? - Roger that.
- 你還在 - 我在
- You survived. - Somewhere...
他們五維空間的某處
...in their fifth dimension.
他們救了我們
They saved us.
是嗎 他們是什麼玩意
Yeah? Who the hell is "They"?
他們又為什麼肯幫我們
And just why would they want to help us'?
我不清楚 但是他們
I don't know, but they
在五維空間裡
constructed this three-dimensional space...
建立了這個三維空間
...inside their five-dimensional reality
好讓你明白該怎麼辦
to allow you to understand it.
可這一點用也沒有
Yeah, that ain't working.
當然有用
Yes, it is.
你看到了時間
You've seen that time is
是以實體方式存在的
represented here as a physical dimension.
你也知道了有種力能跨越時空
You have worked out that you can exert a force across space-time.
引力 用來發送消息嗎
Gravity to send a message.
是的
Affirmative.
引力
Gravity...
可以穿越包括時間在內的維度嗎
...can cross the dimensions, including time.
顯然如此
Apparently.
你有量子數據嗎
Do you have the quantum data?
收到 我有
Roger. I have it.
我試過了所有的波段
I am transmitting it on all wavelengths,
但什麼也沒傳出去 Cooper
but nothing is getting out, Cooper.
我能做到的 我能
I can do this. I can do this.
一個孩子能看懂這麼複雜的資料嗎
But such complicated data to a child?
她可不是普通的孩子
Not just any child.
還有什麼
What else?
拜託 爸爸
Oh, come on, Dad.
Murph 火已經熄滅了 快走啊
Murph, the fire's out! Come on!
就算你在這裡把資料發了出去
Even if you communicate it here,
她也要在好多年以後才能明白
she won't understand its significance for years.
這我清楚 TARS
I get that, TARS.
但我們必須要想出個辦法呀
But we've got to figure something out
否則地球上的人就死定了 想辦法
or the people on Earth are gonna die. Think!
Cooper
Cooper...
他們不是讓我們來改寫歷史的
...they didn't bring us here to change the past.
再說一遍
Say that again.
他們不是讓我們來改寫歷史的
They didn't bring us hereto change the past.
不 根本不是他們讓我們過來的
No, they didn't bring us here at all.
是我們自己
We brought ourselves.
TARS 給我NASA的二進位座標
TARS, give me the coordinates for NASA in binary.
二進位座標 好的 正在轉換資料
In binary. Roger. Feeding data.
那不是幽靈
"It's not a ghost."
那是引力
"It's gravity."
你還沒明白嗎 TARS
Don't you get it yet, TARS?
是我把自己帶到了這裡
I brought myself here!
我們是來和三維空間交流的
We're here to communicate with the three-dimensional world.
我們就是橋樑
We're the bridge!
我以為他們選擇的是我
I thought they chose me.
但他們選的不是我
But they didn't choose me,
- 而是她 - 選她幹什麼 Cooper
- they chose her. - For what, Cooper?
選她去拯救世界
To save the world.
全部的這些 都在這一個小女孩的臥室裡 每一個時刻
All of this is one little girl's bedroom. Every moment.
這是極其複雜的
It's infinitely complex.
他們能通往無盡的時間和空間
They have access to infinite time and space,
但他們與現在沒有任何聯繫
but they're not bound by anything!
他們找不到正確的時間和地點 他們就無法交流
They can't find a specific place in time. They can't communicate.
所以我才來到了這裡 我要找個辦法告訴Murph
That's why I'm here. I'm gonna find a way to tell Murph...
就像我找到了這個時刻一樣
...just like I found this moment.
- 怎麼找呢 Cooper - 愛呀 TARS 用愛
- How, Cooper? - Love, TARS, love.
就像Brand說的 我與Murph的聯繫
It's just like Brand said. My connection with Murph,
是可以量化的 這關係就是關鍵
it is quantifiable. It's the key!
那我們來這裡幹什麼
What are we here to do?
找辦法告訴她
Find how to tell her.
那塊表
The watch.
就是它
That's it.
我們可以把資料轉化成秒針的運動
We code the data into the movement of the second hand.
TARS 把資料轉化成摩爾斯電碼告訴我
TARS, translate the data into Morse and feed it to me.
正在轉化成摩爾斯電碼
Translating data to Morse.
Cooper 如果她不回來了呢
Cooper, what if she never came back for it?
她會回來 她會的
She Will. She Will.
Murph 我看到他的車了
Murph, I can see his car!
他來了 Murph
He's coming, Murph!
好 現在就下去
Okay. I'm coming down.
你怎麼知道
How do you know?
因為那是我給她的
Because I gave it to her.
好的 摩爾斯電碼是點 點 橫 點
Roger. Morse is dot-dot-dash-dot.
點 點
Dot-dot...
橫 點
...dash-dot.
點 橫 點 點
Dot-dash-dot-dot.
橫 橫 橫
Dash-dash-dash.
Dash, dash, dash.
他回來了
He came back!
那就是他 我知道 那就是他
It was him all the time! I knew it!!! It was him!
爸爸回來救我們了
Dad's gonna save us.
我找到了
Eureka!
這是傳統啦
It's traditional.
我找到了
Eureka!
起作用了嗎
Did it work?
我覺得起作用了
I think it might have.
你怎麼知道
How do you know?
因為 他們正在關閉超正方體
Because the bulk beings are closing the tesseract.
你還不懂嗎 TARS
Don't you get it yet, TARS?
他們不是別人
They're not "Beings."
他們就是我們自己
They're us.
我為Murph做的這些事 他們也在為我這麼做
What I've been doing for Murph, they're doing for me.
為我們所有人
For all of us.
Cooper 人類不可能建出這個
Cooper, people couldn't build this.
不 不 不 暫時不能
No. No, not yet.
但總有一天
But one day.
不是你和我 而是人類
Not you and me. But people.
一個進化到超越已知的四維空間的文明
A civilization that's evolved past the four dimensions we know.
現在又怎麼了
What happens now?
Cooper先生
Mr. Cooper.
慢慢來 先生 不要著急 先生
All right. Let's take it slow, sir.
慢慢來 Cooper先生
Nice and easy, Mr. Cooper.
您可不再是精力充沛的小夥子了
Remember, you're no spring chicken anymore.
其實您已經124歲了
Actually, you are 124 years old.
慢慢來 先生
Take it slow, sir.
你 呃 你太幸運了
You were, uh, extremely lucky.
漫遊號發現你時
The Rangers found you
你只剩下幾分鐘的氧氣供給了
with only minutes left in your oxygen supply.
我在哪兒
Where am I?
Cooper空間站
Cooper Station.
目前正在圍繞土星運轉
Currently orbiting Saturn.
Cooper空間站
Cooper Station.
你們能以我來命名它真是太好了
Nice of you to name it after me.
怎麼了
What?
其實空間站不是以您命名的 先生
The station isn't named after you,
它是 呃 以您的女兒命名的
sir. It's, uh, named after your daughter.
不過她一直強調您是非常重要的
Although she's always maintained just how important you were.
她還活著嗎
Is she still alive'?
她幾周後就會到這裡
She'll be here in a couple weeks.
她年紀太大 本不應該在空間站之間奔波
She is far too old to be transferring from another station...
但她聽說有人找到您時
...but when she heard that you'd been found...
您知道Murphy Cooper是多固執的人
...well, this is, uh, Murphy Cooper we're talking about.
那可不
Yes, it is.
我們過幾天會讓您出院
We'll have you checked out of here in a couple days.
這裡的東西一定會讓你很激動
I'm sure you'll be excited to see what's in store.
我其實 呃 在高中時寫過關於您的論文
I actually, uh, did a paper on you in high school.
我知道您在地球上的全部人生
I know all about your life back on Earth.
噢 是嗎 好的
Oh, yeah.
好的
Right.
先生 請跟我來
If-- If you'll follow me,
我們為您準備了非常好的住處
we've got a really good situation for you.
當我向Cooper女士提出這個建議時
So, uh, when I made my suggestion to Miss Cooper...
我很高興地聽說她欣然答應了
...I was delighted to hear that she thought it was perfect.
敬所有勇敢的男人和女人 - 拉撒路 永恆號
這風沙持續不斷 日復一日 塵土飛揚
It was just constant. Just that steady blow of dirt.
當然 我沒有當面向她提議
Of course, I didn't speak to her personally.
我們總是把餐具倒扣著
We always set the plate upside-down.
杯子什麼的 都倒著放
Glasses or cups, whatever it was, upside-down.
我父親是個農民 那時候大家都是農民
Well, my dad was a farmer. Uh, like everybody else back then.
總之 那時的糧食總是不夠
There just wasn't enough food.
我們會用布條
We wore little things, little strips...
掩住口鼻
...of sheet over our nose
防止吸入過多塵土
and mouth so we wouldn't breathe so much of it.
我覺得很興奮 畢竟這是個希望
Well, it was pretty exciting for me because it was hope.
我不管誰說的
I don't care who describes it,
但完全沒有誇張 當時就是那麼糟糕
there is no way for it to be exaggerated. It was that bad.
她也證實 您的確非常喜愛種地
She did confirm just how much you loved farming.
- 是嗎 她這麼說的 - 沒錯
- Oh, she did, did she? - Yeah.
您請
Come here.
好了 歡迎回家 這裡的一切都保持著原來的樣子
Home sweet home. Everything replaced and put back where it...
- 嗨 這個是不是 - 噢 對
- Hey, is this...? - Oh, yeah.
我們在土星周圍發現了您和它
The machine we found out near Saturn when we found you. Yes.
它的電源已經失效了 如果您需要 我們可以給您換一個
Its, uh, power source was shot, but we could get you another one.
好的 拜託了
Yes. Please.
設置
Settings.
通用設置
General settings.
安全設置
Security settings.
誠實度 新設置
Honesty, new setting:
95%
95 percent.
確認 還有其他改動嗎
Confirmed. Additional customization?
幽默度 75%
Humor, 75 percent.
確認
Confirmed.
自毀啟動倒計時 10 9
Auto self-destruct T-minus 10, nine...
還是60%幽默度吧
Let's make that 60 percent.
60% 已確認
Sixty percent confirmed.
- 咚咚咚 - 想被降到55%嗎
- Knock-knock. - You want 55?
從前真是這個樣子的嗎
Is this really what it was like?
從沒這麼乾淨過 小子
It was never this clean, Slick. Heh.
我並不是很在意這樣
I don't care much for
假裝一切回到了當初什麼的
this pretending we're back where we started.
我想知道我們目前的情況
I want to know where we are.
我們對未來的規劃
Where we're going.
Cooper先生 您的家人已經都到了
Mr. Cooper. The family's all in there.
家人
Family?
沒錯 他們都出來見她了
Yeah, they all came out to see her.
她已經低溫休眠將近兩年了
She's been in cryo-sleep for almost two years.
你跟他們說我喜歡種地嗎
You told them I like farming.
那就是我 Murph
It was me, Murph.
我就是你的幽靈
I was your ghost.
我知道
I know.
別人都不相信我
People didn't believe me.
他們都以為那是我一個人的成就
They thought that I was doing it all myself.
可是
But...
我知道那是誰
...I knew who it was.
沒有人相信我
Nobody believed me.
但我知道你會回來
But I knew you'd come back.
怎麼知道
How?
因為我爸爸答應過我了
Because my dad promised me.
我回來了 Murph
Well, I'm here now, Murph.
我回來了
I'm here.
不行
No.
父母不應該看著自己的孩子死去
No parent should have to watch their own child die.
我現在有自己的孩子在這裡陪著
I have my kids here for me now.
你走吧
You go.
去哪裡
Where?
去找Brand
Brand.
她還在太空中
She's out there...
建設營地
...setting up camp.
獨自一人
Alone...
在一個陌生的星系裡
...in a strange galaxy.
艾德蒙斯
或許現在她已經準備好進入長眠
Maybe right now she's settling in for the long nap...
沐浴著新太陽的光芒
...by the light of our new sun...
在我們新的家園裡
...in our new home.
導演 克里斯多夫•諾蘭
編劇 喬納森•諾蘭 和 克里斯多夫•諾蘭
製片人 艾瑪•湯瑪斯
製片人 克里斯多夫•諾蘭
製片人 琳達•奧布斯特
執行製片人 喬丹•哥德伯格 傑克•邁爾斯 基普•索恩 湯瑪斯•圖爾
攝影指導 霍伊特•范•霍伊特瑪
美術指導 納森•克勞利
剪輯 李•史密斯
音樂 漢斯•基默
視覺特效 保羅•佛蘭克林
服裝設計 瑪麗•澤福瑞斯
選角導演 約翰•帕帕席德拉
馬修•麥康納
安妮•海瑟薇
潔西嘉•查斯坦
艾倫•波斯蒂恩
約翰•利特高
以及 邁克爾•凱恩
凱西•阿弗萊克 韋斯•本特利 比爾•艾爾文
麥肯芝•弗伊 托弗•格瑞斯 大衛•吉亞斯
華納兄弟影業 和 派拉蒙影業 連袂出品
傳奇影業 攜手獻映
辛克匹製片公司 / 琳達•奧布斯特製片公司 承制
克里斯多夫•諾蘭 作品
星 際 穿 越